<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Epithalamium Gallo-Britannicum or, Great-Britaines, Frances, and the most parts of Europes vnspeakable ioy, for the most happy vnion, and blessed contract of the high and mighty Prince Charles, Prince of Wales, and the Lady Henrette Maria, daughter to Henry the fourth, sirnamed the Great, late King of the French and Nauarre, and sister to Levvis the thirteenth: now king of the said dominions. Manifesting the royall ancestors and famous progenitors of the mighty Prince Charles, and the most illustrious princesse, the Lady Henrette, explaining the sweete interchanges of mariages, as haue beene betweene France and Great Britaine. ...</title>
            <author>Marcelline, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111979</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847238</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12264</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12264)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 812:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epithalamium Gallo-Britannicum or, Great-Britaines, Frances, and the most parts of Europes vnspeakable ioy, for the most happy vnion, and blessed contract of the high and mighty Prince Charles, Prince of Wales, and the Lady Henrette Maria, daughter to Henry the fourth, sirnamed the Great, late King of the French and Nauarre, and sister to Levvis the thirteenth: now king of the said dominions. Manifesting the royall ancestors and famous progenitors of the mighty Prince Charles, and the most illustrious princesse, the Lady Henrette, explaining the sweete interchanges of mariages, as haue beene betweene France and Great Britaine. ...</title>
                  <author>Marcelline, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 142, [2] p., folded plate : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [at Eliot's Court Press] for Thomas Archer, and are to be sold in Popes Head-Alley, ouer against the signe of the Horse-shooe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: George Marcelline.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Henrietta Maria, --  Queen, consort of Charles I, King of England, 1609-1669 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Epithalamium</hi> Gallo-Britannicum: OR, GREAT-BRITAINES, FRANCES, AND THE moſt parts of <hi>Europes</hi> vnſpeakable Ioy, for the moſt happy Vnion, and bleſſed Contract of the High and Mighty Prince <hi>CHARLES,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> And the LADY HENRETTE MARIA, Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, ſirnamed <hi>the Great, late King of the French and</hi> Nauarre, <hi>and Siſter to</hi> LEVVIS the thirteenth: Now King of <hi>the ſaid</hi> DOMINIONS.</p>
            <p>Manifeſting the royall Anceſtors and famous Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors of the Mighty Prince <hi>CHARLES,</hi> and the moſt Illuſtrious Princeſſe, the Lady HENRETTE, Explaining the ſweete interchanges of Mariages, as haue beene betweene <hi>France</hi> and Great BRITAINE.</p>
            <p>Preſaging the deſtruction and ruine of Antichriſt, the eſtabliſhment of the true Faith, the propagation of the Goſpell, the reſtitution of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of the Enemies deſignes, the erection of Peace, the increaſe of Plentie, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall well-fare of all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Popes Head-Alley,</hi> ouer againſt the ſigne of the Horſe-ſhooe. 1625</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HOPE OF HIS COVNTRIE, THE COMFORT OF HIS FATHER, THE IOY OF HIS FRIENDS, the terrour of his Enemies, the moſt wiſe, valiant, and vertuous Prince;</head>
            <head type="sub">THE MOST HIGH AND Mighty <hi>Charles,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> the ſole Sonne, and chiefe ſolace of the most Potent, Prudent, Pious, Learned, Peaceable, Warlick King IAMES, King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MOſt Mighty Prince; I doubt not but the world may deeme me ouer-audacious, and you this worke te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
<pb facs="tcp:12264:3"/>and troubleſome; the former, that I ſhould preſume to dedicate ſuch an indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, immature Embrio to your Higneſſe; the latter, in regard you Highneſſes eyes haue diuerſity and multitudes of more worthy obiects. To the firſt, J anſwer; that by how much the worke is more meane, by ſo much it hath more need of a mighty Protector, and therefore, though they may deeme me impudent, yet it is not a thing imprudent, but important, that it ſhould ſeeke to ſhelter it ſelfe vnder the patronage of your Highneſſe. To the next, J beſeech your Highneſſe, <hi>(nam nil niſi vota ſuperſunt)</hi> not ſo much to reſpect the weakeneſſe of the worke, as the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe of the Author, to performe duty vnto your mighty Perſonage, who though hee cannot goe for ability, yet he creepeth to offer this Sacrifice vnto you, and is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned through the abundance of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:12264:3"/>loue, to caſt this mite into the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie of your Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>Farre be it from me, with the Ape in the Fable, (who brought her young ones to the Lion, as the moſt amorous and beautifull) to preſent this iſſue of my braines, and off-ſpring of my labours, as worthy of the view of your Highneſſe: Oh no, I am no waies guiltie of ſuch a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lautie, but in regard your royall ſelfe is the Subiect of which it treateth, ſhewing the happineſſe which is deriued by the moſt fortunate contract betweene your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and that moſt incomparable Lady and pure <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin of <hi>France;</hi> in which though with a weake vnable penſile, J haue drawne forth and portraied the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine parts of your princely Perſonages; of the which, though all knew ſome, yet ſome knew not all which J haue related: in the which deſcription and map of your
<pb facs="tcp:12264:4"/>perfections if I haue failed, (as J cannot hope to the contrary) I humbly craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and proſtrate my ſelfe at the feet of your mercifull cenſure; beſeeching you that the true affection of the Author may couer the imperfection of the worke.</p>
            <p>The reaſons which moued me to this boldneſſe to craue your Highneſſe his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, were theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect you are the chiefe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of this Marriage Song, the which Subiect though it be impoſsible for mee to honour by my worke, yet it is moſt certaine, my worke is honoured by it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard as you, for all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are the adamant of admiration from all men, ſo moſt eſpecially for your reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vertue of humility, who though you be high in Maieſty, yet you are low in minde, and deſpiſe not, but incourage men, though weake &amp; impotent, in any good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes
<pb facs="tcp:12264:4"/>and vertuous endeuours, that ſo being nouriſhed by your fauour, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with your countenance, they might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and grow in goodneſſe, and in fine attaine to the ſumme of all perfections.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, J know that I doe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly owe my labours and all that J haue to your Highneſſe who are the Conduit, by which God conueys felicity not only to me, but Millions of people; the which conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee in gratitude to conſecrate this worke vnto you.</p>
            <p>Reiect not therefore theſe fruits of my Induſtry, which were inuented &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented out of meere reſpect to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the ioy conceiued for the late contract with <hi>France;</hi> and as you are the patterne of all vertues, ſo vouchſafe to bee the Patron of this booke, which is but an abridgement &amp; the compendium of them, &amp; an expreſsion of the happineſſe, which is
<pb facs="tcp:12264:5"/>likely to be an attendant and follower of this your intended and promiſed mariage with the Lady <hi>Henrette Maria,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, King of the French &amp; Nauarre, &amp; Siſter to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth, now French King; the which grieuing to ſee, that none more able than my ſelfe would vndertake, J (though with weakeneſſe) haue performed.</p>
            <p>Let therefore this booke which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten onely for your Highneſſe, is Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your Highneſſe, be accepted of your Highneſſe; of the which, not deſpairing, J wiſh vnto your Highneſſe a higher than the higheſt Happineſſe, that you may haue a long and fortunate life, remaine the comforter of your friends, the Conquerer of your enemies, and be the Father of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny happy Children.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſſe moſt obſeruant,</hi> George Marcelline.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MOST IL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVSTRIOVS AND euery waies accompliſht Prince,</hi> George, <hi>Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>Viſcount</hi> Villers, <hi>Baron of</hi> Whaddon, <hi>Lord High Admirall of</hi> England, <hi>Iuſtice in Eyre of all his Maieſties</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, Parkes, and Chaſes beyond <hi>Trent,</hi> Maſter of the Horſe to his Maieſtie, and one of the Gentlemen of his Maieſties Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter, and one of his Maieſties moſt honourable Priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of England and Scotland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt honoured Prince; let it be no wonder vnto your Grace, why I doe implore your Ioynt Patronage with your Prince, of theſe my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb facs="tcp:12264:6"/>ſith you are his <hi>Ionathan,</hi> and haue beene a companion and faithfull friend vnto him in all his Trauells; manifeſting your ſelfe to bee as faithfull to that Sonne, as you were fauoured of the Father. As therefore you were his Aſſociate in his Peregrination, ſo ioyne with him in the Patronizing of this worke: Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as you were a chiefe inſtrument of hindring the mariage with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and furthering this with <hi>France,</hi> by which meanes, you brought happineſſe vnto this Iland, for the which, it yeeldeth vnto your Grace; ſo alſo you are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this worke, and a ioynt Subiect of it; vouchſafe therefore to be a ioynt Patron of it.</p>
            <p>A fourth Motiue which encourageth me in this requeſt, is, that as you are the chiefe Fauourite of our King on earth, and of God the King of Kings, ſo you are aprincipall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer of all good and worthy proceedings, by which your name is embalmed with fame, and your memory will bee immortall. Not doubting therefore but you will grace this worke with milde acceptance, though not for the manner of writing, yet the matter written of in it, I ceaſe to trouble you, but alwaies reſt an humble ſuiter to your grace for accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb facs="tcp:12264:6"/>and to God, for the continuance of your happineſſe in the preſent, and your increaſe of it in the future, that you may bee bleſſed inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, externally, and eternally, and that the higheſt would multiplie all temporall and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces vpon your Grace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humbly deuoted,</hi> George Marceline.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, (I hope I ſhall not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call thee) the ioy conceiued by mee for this contract, the loue to my Country, the zealous affection I beare to the vertues of our hopefull Prince, and his happy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, haue ioyntly enforced mee to vndertake this Enterprize; in the which, though many calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting cenſures may blame my Pen, yet they muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Perſons handled in it; in the blazing of whoſe perfections, if they tax me with flattery, they brand themſelues with follie, and an ill affection to their King, Prince, and Countrey, and manifeſt themſelues either to haue their eares ſtopt, and their eyes blinded, or their Iudgements defectiue; for they ought to account it their chiefeſt honour, to honour (if it bee poſsible to adde honour to their names, whoſe vertues honour themſelues, more than lieth in the power of any Pen to honour them) their
<pb facs="tcp:12264:7"/>ſoueraigne, and his onely Sonne, and our onely hope; But ſure I am, that multitudes will loue and honour this worke, if it be onely for the Subiects handled in it, the loue of whoſe worth may claime an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant looke on theſe my labours; in which are ſhewed the fortunate conſequences likely to enſue vpon this contract, which are the deſtruction of the Foes of Chriſt, and the Enemies of Chriſtians, the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of the Truth, the Peace of the Church, the proſperity of all people; which ſheweth, though in an Epitome, the vertues of thy King, the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Father, in the enioying of ſuch a ioyous Sonne, as the mighty Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> whoſe names offer not ſo much as to reade without a true loue ioynd with a trembling feare, for it is they, by whoſe meanes thou doſt enioy thy meanes, vpon whoſe life dependeth thy welfare: rather therefore ſhew thy wiſedome in ſilence, for if thou termeſt me a Paraſite, thou proueſt thy ſelfe a Parrat which ſpeakeſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Epithalamium Gallo-Britannicum,</hi> OR GREAT BRITTAINES And FRANCES <hi>Joy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Felicitie of a Kingdome is placed in the Proſperitie of the Prince; and the welfare of a Prince, either made or mangled in his Matching: But neuer was Kingdome more happie in a Prince, neuer Prince more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate in his Choyce, than the Treaſure and Store-houſe of our hopes, the Summe and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our future bliſſe, the high and mightie Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> in obtaining this Princeſſe, who vnparalell'd for perfections, both externall of her bodie, and internall of her minde, ſtands as a matchleſſe Mirrour to all her Sex, if not to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12264:9"/>be adored, yet at the leaſt admired, hath made a Contract between three Kingdomes and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which were a long time diuorced from it; being like the houſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> troubled vntill their <hi>Iſaak</hi> had found out a <hi>Rebecca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Peereleſſe Prince! fortunate beyond the imagination of mans minde, then ſurely more tranſcending the limits of my pens relation; could you but pry into the hearts of millions of people, you ſhould ſee all the veines &amp; ſtreets of thoſe Metropolitan Cities of thoſe little worlds, ſwell'd and full with ioy, who formerly found no tranquillitie of minde, though in the peace of the State; becauſe your Royall Selfe had not found out a Second Selfe, whereby their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie might ſhroud and refreſh themſelues here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, vnder the ſhadow of your Branches, and that from your Iſſue, fountaines of fortunate ioy might flow to ſucceeding ages. How many Kingdomes doe bathe themſelues in the ſunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of ſolace, and finde more than earthly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, in thoſe reſplendent beames, which ſhine from this bleſſed Contract: conceiuing no leffe ioy in your relinquiſhing of the Ladie <hi>Maria</hi> of Spaine, and matching and vniting your Soule (which is the Court of the Higheſt,
<pb facs="tcp:12264:9"/>and King of Kings, the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt) vnto the heart of that vnparalell'd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, the Ladie <hi>Henrette Maria</hi> of France, which is a rich Cabinet, fill'd with the Gemms and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualuable Iewels, of morall vertues and diuine graces.</p>
            <p>If it pleaſe your hopefull Highneſſe to retire a little from home, and to caſt an eye of conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration vpon France, there may be ſeene ſuch an infinite ineffable meaſure of mirth, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable treaſure of true ioy, found by them in this Coniunction, and from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the Peere to the poore, nothing but applauſe and triumph. For can they chuſe but reioyce, to ſee that Vertues Paramour and Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Venus,</hi> whoſe vertue ennobleth her birth, whoſe birth doth make her vertues eminent, whoſe countenance and whoſe conditions doe mutually grace and adome each other, ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily beſtowed; and their perfectly accompliſht Princeſſe, vnited to ſo glorious, ſo gracious a Head, as who is the Ioy of his Friends, the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his Enemies, the Comfort and Hope of his Country, the Patterne of Princes, the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the world, the mightie Prince <hi>Charles?</hi> For what Countrey could haue beene the Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12264:10"/>of ſuch a Prince; or what Prince the Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of ſuch a Countrey, as Great Brittaine of <hi>Charles,</hi> or <hi>Charles</hi> of Great Brittaine? the which, as Hee is bleſt with all graces, ſo it aboundeth with all bleſſings, that He might be happie in it, and it fortunate in Him; that as He bleſſeth that with peace, ſo it might ſatisfie Him with plenty. Had ſhe forſaken a fat fruitfull ſoile to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a barren Countrey, it might ſomewhat haue impaired her happineſſe, and beene a wound to her welfare; but this is a Paradiſe of pleaſure, a Land like Canaan, flowing with milke and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Had ſhe found ſuch a fertile Kingdome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of ſo royall a Prince, ſhee could not haue had ſo much ioy in the one, without enioying the other: if the ring be void of a precious ſtone, it is not ſo much eſteemed; neither hath a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond ſet in lead, ſuch ſtore of luſter: But our Prince, ſeated and planted in ſuch a pleaſant place, is like a Diamond ſet in Gold, the one of which makes the other of more eſtimation.</p>
            <p>Oh fortunate France! if thou doeſt not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue thy happineſſe, that art linked in the bond of amitie with faire Albion, whoſe climate is temperate, whoſe aire ſerene and cleare; here is not heat ſo exceſſiuely parching in Summer,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12264:10"/>but that any conſtitution may endure it, nor the cold ſo piercing in Winter, but that the moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may withſtand it. How many Cryſtall fountaines and running ſtreames bee there, like ſo many veines in this bodie of our Kingdome? and to the intent that none of the elements might be defectiue, but that all might concurre to make vs happie, wee are ſufficiently ſtored with all kinde of fuell and firing; neither is the wombe of our earth barren, but moſt fit for conception, multiplies the ſeed committed to it, ſo that our fields doe laugh with ſtore of graine, and Autumne crams our barnes with full increaſe; ſo that our Countrey-mans life is crowned with contentment. And whereas in other Nations they haue no want, here they haue no feare of want; for what commoditie haue wee not, either to comfort our ſelues, or helpe our neighbours? What bleſſings doe we not enioy, either neceſſarie to our ſubſiſtence, or requiſite to our well-being? no ſurely, and I may well ſay, The Lord hath not dealt ſo with any Nation; for how doe wee abound with ſtore of corne and cattle, and all other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities? or if we ſhould want any thing for feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie (although we haue all indeed for neceſſitie)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12264:11"/>yet how fitly is it ſeated for all kinde of traffique, and as (who ſhould ſay) it were the onely Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Sea, it is lullabide in the lap of <hi>Thetis,</hi> and hugged in with the <hi>Ocean,</hi> who doth ſo enwrap her in her armes, as ſhe doth not onely permit her trading and commerce with all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but doth promiſe to ſaue and ſecure her from her enemies. Them who can preſcribe bounds vnto the ioy of the French Nation, who ſee their Princeſſe, the Glorie of her Sex, ſo well and worthily matched, that it is to be expected from her wombe ſhall iſſue mightie Monarchs, who ſhall bee the moſt happie Princes in the world in their inheritance; whoſe lot is like to fall in ſo faire a Land, the which is a Treaſurie and Store-houſe fraught with all bleſſings, which denies no kinde of ſuſtenance to her inhabitants.</p>
            <p>But if you leaue the Citie, and examine but the Citizens, forſake the ſuruey of the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and looke vpon the Contents; and you ſhall haue ioyfull experience, that the place is not ſo pleaſant, but the people as pleaſing; and from him that is ſeated in the royall throne of dignitie, to him that lieth groueling in the deepe abyſſe of miſerie, all full of affabilitie and
<pb facs="tcp:12264:11"/>courteſie. If you inquire into the diſpoſtion of the ſacred Maieſtie of our moſt mightie and inuict Monarch, vnder the wings of whoſe wiſdome we his ſubiects take moſt quiet repoſe and reſt; you ſhall finde him to be repleat with all graces requiſite for ſo great, ſo gracious a Soueraigne: within whoſe countenance like two heauenly lamps ſhine both Maieſtie and Mercy, that the one might win from his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects a reuerent feare, the other obtaine a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious loue; whoſe minde is fraught with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane knowledge, and furniſht with diuine, in ſuch a meaſure and manner, as he may not be more truly ſtiled <hi>The King of Great Britaine,</hi> than <hi>The Salomon of Kings:</hi> whoſe paſſions are ſubiect to reaſon, whoſe reaſons Pilot is Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; who will not iniure himſelfe by ſuffering exceſſe, nor offend any in offering the leaſt wrong vnto them; who though he truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the ſtile of a <hi>Peace-maker,</hi> yet hee doth not reſpect peace ſo much as to neglect a iuſt occaſion of warre; who as he is not like a raw wound, too ſenſible or apprehenſiue of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſo he is not like dead fleſh, void of all fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; who as he is ſo conſcionable not to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize, ſo he is ſo couragious not to permit a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb facs="tcp:12264:12"/>to vſurpe his owne or his friends domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for though his anger did a long time ſleepe, yet being awaked out of ſlumber, Hee will not eaſily be ſtilled. The running rough ſtreames which be ſoone diſturbed, are moſt ſhallow; but the deepe places which are not ſo ſpeedily moued, are more profound. The ſhrubs, bruſh and ſtubble, though they be kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in an inſtant, yet they are extinct in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when heart of Oake and ſtout Timber, though it be not ſo ſoone accended, yet as it is more ſolid, ſo it is of longer continuance. To be ſoone inflamed, is a ſigne of Raſhneſſe; but alwayes to beare iniuries, is want of Valour: Therefore this our royall religious King, to the end that he might be as well void of temeritie as timiditie, of follie as of feare, will not be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but vpon iuſt occaſion, nor ſtilled without due recompence.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe that Wiſdome for a long time kept his ſword in his ſheath, yet Iuſtice hath now drawne it: He knowes that Raſhneſſe is the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortiue fruit of Paſſion, and the bloud of his ſubiects precious; therefore He poiſeth all his proiects in the balance of diſcretion, Hee weigheth all his iniuries with his reuenge; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12264:12"/>to ſhew the ripeneſſe of his iudgement, he will not ſuffer his hand to be the author of any raw action, which is not thorowly diſgeſted with due premeditation; whom though none can conquer in loue, yet he doth loue in wiſdome; who though he did ſeeme a while to winke at his childrens misfortunes, yet Lion-like he did <hi>obdormire apertis oculis,</hi> and ſaw the iniurie done by others, and the miſerie endured by them; of the which ſince peace cannot be the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian to preuent a iuſt warre, he will make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment if a warre can beget a iuſt peace; who hath ſhewed more magnanimitie in dangerleſſe deſpiſing, than many in dangerous affecting others kingdomes, being very loth to hazzard the loſſe of guiltleſſe ſoules, or to build vpon his neighbours ruines, but like a wiſe Pilot to gouerne the ſhip well in which God had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, and not to ſeeke to be a head to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers body. Neither was this for the defect of any fortitude; oh no, there are like to be enow bleeding witneſſes of his kingly courage, and he is moſt wiſe to ſee what is beſt, and moſt iuſt to performe what he ſees. Indeed our potent King doth meaſure his greatneſſe by his goodneſſe, and only affecteth greatneſſe that he may haue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12264:13"/>meanes to exerciſe his goodneſſe; the grauitie of whoſe head is adorned with the grace of his heart, for he hath not only the name, but the nature of a King, and vſeth not his Kingdome as Tenants at will doe their houſes, who care not how they be ruinated, becauſe each day they expect a departure out of them; but as if he had an eternall leaſe, he ſeeketh the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all welfare of it; for his ſword is at enmitie with thoſe which are foes to vertue, and his purſe at peace with them which are enemies to vice. His Subiects taſte not the bitter fruits of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous taxation; neither are Lawes with vs ſo much made to finde faults, as to preuent and puniſh them: Our Court is not a priuiledged place of vnlawfull actions and licenciouſneſſe, but is the reſident and abiding place of Him, which as Hee is the Father of his Countrey, ſo He giueth it good example: and who is moſt bountifull in rewarding the well-deſeruing, and in requiting courteſies; for Hee knowes ſufficiently, that to be indebted, is to be an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour: and hath a moſt diligent care, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diligence, in his words and his works, to inſtruct his people, hauing life in his doctrine, and doctrine in his life; for He appeares to his
<pb facs="tcp:12264:13"/>Subiects vertuous, as He would haue them be, and labours to be ſuch as He appeareth, that as his Lawes giue life vnto his people, ſo he giueth life to his Lawes; for they be but as Maximes, deriued &amp; collected out of his life; for it is as a great Volume, in which they may reade whole Lectures of wholeſome Precepts. Neither doth He driue his Subiects on the path of Vertue, ſo much with the Rod of Law, as He doth draw them with the Adamant of Loue; for, can they chuſe, but dearely and nearely affect Him, who, as Hee is aboue them in place, ſo Hee exceeds them in loue? who, being the Head, cannot ſee one of the members hurt, but Hee doth ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize in ſorrow with it, not placing his gaines in their paines, or eſteeming Himſelfe moſt a King, when they are moſt baſely ſubiected.</p>
            <p>Neither is his Eſtate with the peoples welfare, as it were in an vniuſt ballance, ſo that his goes higheſt, when theirs goes loweſt; but the ſeat of all his happineſſe is ſituated in their good fortunes. Neither doth Hee rule them with a Rod of Iron, but a Scepter of Gold, neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining their libertie, vnleſſe it tended to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenciouſneſſe; nor pulling goods from any particular, vnleſſe it were for a generall good.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12264:14"/>In fine, Hee hath brought all his Subiects to ſuch a paſſe, that though He takes nothing by force, yet He hath all by loue; for who would not venture, either his purſe or his perſon, to performe his pleaſure? which of his Subiects would not entertaine his death with ſweet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracement, ſo that his Princes, or Soueraignes Succeſſours and Poſterities welfare, might haue birth from his death, and ſpring out of his aſhes? Certes, there is none but would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhake hands with life, libertie, or eſtate, in a gratefull requitall of thoſe bleſſings we here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, by the meanes of his Maieſties moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gouernment. Indeed they are ſo vnited vnto him, by the inviolable bonds of feare and loue, that all his Subiects, as his Pulſes, doe beat according to the motion of his heart: For ought not they willingly to performe his will, who denieth to grant none of their wiſhes; for hath his Kingdomes deſired peace? how long haue they poſſeſt it? yea, in ſuch a turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent time, when almoſt all Europe hath had warre in her owne bowels. But doe our people thirſt for reuenge vpon thoſe which haue iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Soueraignes Iſſue, and wronged the Princely Branches ſprung from their Royall
<pb facs="tcp:12264:14"/>Stocke, for feare they ſhould not be deliuered of that which they trauell of, but loſe their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging? Hee aſſumeth Armes for the reſtauration of his Sonne, to doe that by force, which Hee could not purchaſe by fauour.</p>
            <p>And ſithence He findeth his Enemies not to be like Flints, which may be broken vpon the feather-bed of perſwaſions; but as Nettles, the which, by how much more they are eaſily handled, by ſo much the more violently they ſting; He reſolues to handle them more rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leſt they as much hurt him, as they iniured his Neighbours. Then ſurely, what vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ioy ought this to be, to that matchleſſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of France and all her Nation, She not more reioycing, that Shee hath found ſuch a royall, wiſe, and euerie way accompliſht Father, than they, that they haue found ſuch a noble wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Friend? She may exult that She is ingrafted into ſuch a Stocke, they of ſuch Alliance; for He is not onely potent in men, but powerfull in money and munition, that as his money wants not men, ſo his men want not money. Howſoeuer, indeed, ſome may ſuggeſt and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, that his bountie hath almoſt exhauſt his Treaſurie: Yet, as the candle, though it giues
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12264:15"/>another light, yet it ſelfe is not darkened: So, though our Soueraigne hath enricht many of his Subiects, yet Hee hath not impoueriſht Himſelfe; for Hee hath ſo beſtowed it vpon ſuch perſons, as were not ſo willing to receiue it, but they will be as well content to ſurrender it vp into his hands againe, if either their Kings pleaſure, or their Countries profit, giue them ſummons to make ſuch a redeliuerie. Then ſurely, not onely the Throne, but the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, not onely the French Prince, but the People may ſwimme (I had almoſt ſaid) ſurfet with delight in this Bleſſed Vnion; for what hindrance is there, whereby that moſt Chriſtian King, <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth, may expect, but that as our Princes Highneſſe ioynes hands with his Siſter, ſo our Kings Maieſtie will ioyne Armes with him, for the regaining of thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which vniuſtly an vſurping hand detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from him? for, <hi>Vis vnitafortior,</hi> and (that I may vſe our Prouerbe) <hi>Many hands make light worke;</hi> Diuerſe threds twiſted together, as they doe more ſtrongly binde, ſo they are not ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily broken of an enemie. It was King <hi>Richards</hi> compariſon, A bundle of arrowes bound toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could not be broken; but diſſeuered, with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12264:15"/>much facilitie they may be cracked: and I may make application to theſe Kingdomes, as Hee did to that his Kingly Iſſue. It is not to bee doubted, but that ſince <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Lewis,</hi> two Kings ſo valiant; Great Brittaine and France, two Kingdomes ſo potent; are vnited and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this bond, as well of affection as affinitie; their enemies ſhall not bee of power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice them, nor of ſtrength to withſtand them. And howſoeuer the whole world is an eie-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the beautie and bountie of both their mindes, which is ſo great, that each of them doe eſteeme it a greater honour, to giue a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, than to get it; yet where there is wrong offered them and their Allies, all the might of their foes ſhall be as a ſtone daſht againſt ſteele, which ſhall rebound in their owne faces, to their owne diſgrace and ruine.</p>
            <p>Neither let their enemies thinke, but that howſoeuer they doe not loue to ſeeke others Dominions, yet they will not loſe their owne without ſtirring: For will our dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, when both amitie and equitie, religion and affection doe giue him loud ſummons to reſtore his children to their inheritance, detaine his helping hand from his hopefull iſſue? Will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12264:16"/>He or can He ſee without ſorrow (and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, labour to redreſſe it) that his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Countrey, which formerly was the garden of the world, vnpeopled, ruinated, and made a deſolate Deſart; his Iſſue to be exiled from their inheritance, and hope baniſhed from them; his childrens children forced to flie before they were taught to goe; Can he, I ſay, ſee this, and not ſorrow at it? Can he ſorrow at it, and yet ſuffer it? Can he haue power, and yet want will to reuenge it? Oh no, his hand is full of vigour, and hee is fraught with valour; his ſubiects ſoules doe thirſt for reuenge, and all his foes ſhall haue wofull experience, that he is as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant to maintaine a warre, as wiſe to entertaine a peace, and he can as well ſacrifice at the altars of <hi>Mars</hi> as <hi>Ceres,</hi> and is as well <hi>Achilles</hi> for his courage, as <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> for his counſell. Then who can impoſe a period to the endleſſe ioy of the French Nation, who haue found a way to ioyne themſelues with ſuch a powerful Prince, who doth not only make them happy in his alliance, but is likely to make them alſo fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in conqueſts and victories, when theſe two mighty Monarchs ſhall mutually aid each other to right themſelues, their wronged
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12264:16"/>neighbours, and affinitie? Thus farre haue I proceeded in the narration of the neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently extolled perfections of our mightie Monarch, in ſo much as my penne is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded ſhee hath wronged them in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and made but an imperfect draught of them, being vnable to limme them to the life. From whence <hi>France</hi> may vnderſtand, that her happineſſe is higher aſcended, in regard their Princeſſe is ioyned in wedlocke with one which is ſo worthily deſcended from one who is the moſt potent, moſt prudent, moſt wiſe, moſt valiant, moſt magnanimous, magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Monarch that euer bleſt the aire with a breath, or theſe kingdomes with a peaceable, yet proſperous gouernment, as if he had beene only ſent from Heauen to increaſe Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and this Kingdomes welfare.</p>
            <p>But as if God had not onely intended to bleſſe that illuſtrious Princeſſe with ſuch a royall Father who doth grace the fruit which is borne of him, he hath alſo prouided a Prince to be her husband, which doth adorne the ſtocke he comes of, who heires his Father not only in his royall rich powerfull kingdomes, but in his rare perfect accompliſht qualities; at
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12264:17"/>whoſe birth the Senate-houſe of the Planets did ioyntly conſent and determine to conferre both vpon his body and minde all the perfections that can accompany a corporall eſſence, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit in a mortall manſion place; at whoſe Birth-day Dame Nature brought her richeſt ornaments to decke him withall, and all the Grace tooke poſſeſſion of him for their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and to the intent good education might nouriſh and cheriſh thoſe ſeeds ſo ſowne, hee was not nuſled and nurſed in the night of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, nor weaned ouer-ſoone from the paps of knowledge: But the good inſtructions of faithfull Tutors, the godly example of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious King, did continually ſo blow the ſparks, of vertue that Dame Nature had kindled in him, as in ſmall time they gaue forth their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt heat, ſetting on fire, and inflaming the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of all that knew him: Whoſe bodie, as it was compoſed of the pureſt mold that lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the boſome of Nature, ſo it was built vp in the ſtatelieſt frame and faſhion that can bee imagined, wanting nothing that the Heauenly Influences could infuſe into it; ſo that indeed he ſeemeth the Maſter-peece of Nature, as if ſhe had aimed at a reach aboue herſelfe, and when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12264:17"/>ſhe produced him, intended to frame and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Angell.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, ſeeing it is not fitting, that a poore man of meane eſtate ſhould inhabit the Court of a King; for ſo the roomes might bee ruined for want of imployment, and it would ſeeme like a painted Sepulcher, God put in an Inhabitant, anſwerable to that ſtatelineſſe of the building, and rareneſſe of the edifice; and leſt it might ſeem to be nothing but wals with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out furniture, God put ſuch a ſoule into it, ſo adorned and beautified with all perfect graces, and gracious perfections, that the one might bee correſpondent to the other, in eminencie and dignitie, whoſe minde is of ſufficient power to informe each part and organ of his bodie; ſo his bodie is able to performe whatſoeuer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble action his minde ſhall incite and moue him to it, being both of abilitie and agilitie, to put in execution the Soules directions. Hee which hath a weake bodie and ſtrong minde, which pricks him forward to valiant actions, is like a woman, which hath not ſtrength to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of that which ſhee hath conceiued: But on the contrarie, corporall ſtrength without men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall courage, is as a ſeruant which wants a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12264:18"/>to ſet him on worke: But our noble Prince hath both ſtoutneſſe of ſtomach and ſtrength of bodie to put in execution euerie valiant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe his minde pricks him forward to, ſo that no man which ſucketh in this vitall aire, is able to performe any warlike action, either on horſe or on foot more ſtrongly, or deliuer that ſtrength more nimbly, or become that deliuerie more gracefully, than our hopefull valiant Prince. His ſtature of bodie is neither a Giant or a Pigmie, but placed in the golden in cane, to each eyes cenſure He ſeemeth an obiect of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. In a word, each particle of euerie part of his bodie, is ſo voyd of deformitie, and ſo full of the beſt workmanſhip of Nature, that Hee may ſeeme a Prince of all, as well for his beauty as his birth: And had he nothing but a body, it were ſufficient to command the beſt mans approbation and affection; for his countenance is an Epitome of Ethicks, in which Modeſtie and Maieſtie doe fight for ſuperioritie, and <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> to bee in contention for the higher places, yet ſtriuing in ſuch faſhion, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, or their Dominions, are dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but inlarged by theſe their warres: But if you make a further ſearch, &amp;c leauing his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12264:18"/>looke into his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, you ſhall finde the former, compared to this, to be but as an Index of a great Volome of Vertue, in the which Center they all reſt in their higheſt perfection: and howſoever in moſt men hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie doth ſildo me accompanie honour, and lowlineſſe of minde highneſſe of eſtate; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in Him it is farre other way to: for though He be aduanced to the higheſt pitch of honour, yet He ſcorneth to ſcorne any thing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or to diſdaine ought but baſeneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, it is alwayed his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, rather to comfort than to contemne the poore; and as He is full of humilitie, for He is void of pride, aſpiring to nothing but goodneſſe: and leſt that He, being a Prince to ſo many, ſhould be a ſlaue to Himſelfe, He continually ſubdues his paſſions, and gets the conqueſt of them, Hee knowes that anger is a ſhort madneſſe, &amp; mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a long anger; and therefore Hee reſolues to lodge no furie in his boſome, and is neuer ſicke of this frenzie, onely indeed Hee may be ſomtimes tranſported with a god by zeale, whin either Hee seem his Countrey iniured, or his God diſhonoured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for Hee accounted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his chiefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:12264:19"/>and reuerence the other. It is a rare thing to ſee a Prince that hath all ſtore of delicates (for wee are readie to rot our ſelues with ryot, being put into a delightſome great paſture of plentie) not ſubiect to ſurfets: but He doth neuer drinke, but to allay the heat and thirſt of Nature; nor eate, but to ſatisfie and mortifie hunger; from which temperancie of diet, his matchleſſe ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe chaſtitie hath birth: For, whereas that man which is ſuperfluous in his diet, is laſciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in his thought, becauſe Vncleanneſſe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the childe of Ryot; Hee therefore, that He might not be ſtained with the one, abſtains from the other, to the end that his Heart (which is Gods Temple) might not be made a Den of theeues; for when the Body faſteth the Soule feaſteth, and the earthly members being morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the faculties of the Soule doe grow more liuely and powerfull.</p>
            <p>Thus being Maſter of his owne luſts, Hee ſcornes to be a ſeruant to his ſubſtance; but at his pleaſure can part from it, and turne it out of his ſeruice, yet neuer but vpon a iuſt occaſion; for that were to haue too little and light reſpect of his ſeruant, being a meere prodigalitie; but when Hee ſeeth it requiſite, for the reward of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12264:19"/>Vertue, or the maintenance of Honour, to part from it, the Sunne is not more liberall of his light at high noone-day, than He of his meanes: for Hee loues not money like your couetous man (whoſe eyes are out, and he can neuer ſee when he hath ſufficient, who like a <hi>Danaïdum dolium</hi> is neuer fill'd or ſatisfied,) but onely for neceſſitie, like a wife Mariner prouiding in a calme againſt the comming of a ſtorme, and in the ſunne-ſhine of peace, preparing to welcome the turbulent tempeſtuous time of warre. And for his wiſdome (as who ſhould ſay, it were likely Hee ſhould bee in nothing vnlike to his father) He outrunneth his age, and leaueth all thoſe of his yeeres behinde Him in knowledge; for Hee ſitteth in counſell like a ſage Senatour, and a Law-making <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> that it ſeemeth a wonder (but wonders are no wonders in a wondrous ſubiect) how in the bloſſome of his yeeres He ſhould haue ſuch ripeneſſe and matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Iudgement, and in his greene youth bee ſuch a graue Counſellour: For did not his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Highneſſe, in the laſt Parliament, not only in appearance, but in truth, ſo well prouide for the ſafetie and ſecuritie, both of his Friends and Countrey, that Hee was generally applauded
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12264:20"/>both of Counſellours and Commons, as being the moſt wiſe and watchfull Prince, for the welfare of his people: Firſt, ſhewing his ardent zeale to Gods Glorie and Religion, to make wholſome ſalutiferous Lawes, for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Sowers of Sedition, and the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minglers of the tares of their owne inuentions, amongſt the pure graine of Gods Word. And thus hauing expreſt his loue to God (aboue all vnder God) He prouides for his Peoples proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, enacts Lawes, as Antidotes againſt former exactions, ſo cuſtomarily and vnconſcionably practiſed in this our Common-wealth; as if He were ſoly and wholly happie in making his people fortunate, and in eaſing them of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthens of oppreſſion impoſed vpon them, bound vpon their backs, and laid vpon their ſhoulders. And indeed there neuer was Prince in Chriſtendome, more commended by mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men in ſpeeches, or commended to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall God in prayers, than is our mightie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uict Prince; whoſe worth is ſuch, that if I ſhould liue to the age of <hi>Neſtor,</hi> and in the whole courſe of my life doe nought but praiſe Him; praiſe Him in nothing but that which He is worthie of: vtter his worth compendiouſly,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12264:20"/>yet my pen would ſtill bee a debter to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts; for He is not like the vulgar ſort (as the vulgar Prouerbe tels vs) <hi>Conſtant in nothing but inconſtancie;</hi> but his minde once fixed on a worthie obiect, is like a Starre which moueth not out of her orbe; but is euer the ſame in her motion. The little ſhrubs are ſhaken with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric little puffe of winde, but the ſtately Cedar, which is firmely rooted and faſtned in the ground, as it is more noble, ſo it is more ſtable. Many Feathers and Weather-cocks in our daies, who are not reſolute in any determinations, or determinate in any reſolution, doe in an inſtant loathe that which they haue loued: but our Prince, as He doth not lightly ſettle affection, ſo He will not eaſily remoue it; for He deemes the one a defect of wiſdome, the other an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of wauering, and an ouer-plus of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie.</p>
            <p>Therefore, Hee being alwayes balanced and counterpoyſed with due premeditation in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, cannot be induced in an inſtant to relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh and diſtaſte that which Hee affecteth. Then hath not France great reaſon and cauſe of ioy and exultation, who hath found out ſuch a Mate for their incomparable Princeſſe?
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12264:21"/>who is one which hath ſtoutneſſe and courage of minde, ioyned to the ſtrength of his bodie, wiſdome accompanying his valour, vertue his ſoule; who is a Prince as well in worth as birth, excelling in bountie and beautie, and in all his actions obſeruing the golden meane; who is conſtant in his loue, firme in his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whoſe worth few can conceiue, no man vtter, all men may admire; the deſcent of whoſe bloud doth ennoble his birth, the excellencie of whoſe birth doth enthronize and dignifie his vertues; whoſe vertues (as I may ſo ſay) doe almoſt Deifie his Soule; the ineſtimable price of whoſe Soule doth adorne his bodie, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting in it; the rare temper of whoſe bodie doth bleſſe his ſoule, by being the Manſion-place of it. And thus Hee which hath all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, is to be all Hers, and that Princeſſe to bee bleſt with the admirable conſtitution of his bodie, and the incomparable condition of his minde. Had his body been of vnequall vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable mixture by the elements, the ſoule might haue loathed ſuch a muddie building, &amp; would ſoone haue forſaken her habitation; or hath the minde beene corrupt and filthie, it would ſoone haue ruinated the rare bodie, in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12264:21"/>regard it would haue employed it to ſuch ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ruinous courſes, as it would ſoone haue produced her ouerthrow, and demoliſht this mortall Edifice of Nature; by which meanes and likelyhood, the ſhortneſſe of the Princes life, might haue made an abridgement of her happineſſe, and haue cut ſhort the continuance of her ioyes; but Nature hath ſo tempered and framed Him, of ſuch an equall proportion of heat and moyſture, that the exceſſiue heat of the one doth not threaten a Combuſtion, nor the abundance of the other a Deluge: but for his complexion Hee may bee another <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> and She moſt ſuperlatiue of her Sex in all felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in the poſſeſſion of ſo louing a Husband, ſo long a time, as He is like to inioy this vital tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie vncertaine breath. Had He beene like a Roſe, or a Flower De-luce, which though they bee faire things, yet they are of ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: (for the one is no ſooner blowne, but it ſheddeth; &amp; the other fadeth in the bud) her ioy might haue found ſorrow in the fear of the loſſe of her Ioy; but He alreadie is growne to ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and we hope (as may be coniectured, both by the temper of his bodie, &amp; temperance of his minde) is not onely pleaſing to the eye, but is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12264:22"/>alſo likely to be a laſting fruit. It is the office of an husband to liue with his wife as a man of knowledge, and what Prince wiſer than his Highneſſe, who ſquares out all his actions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of Gods Word? who is ſo verſt in each verſe of Scripture, ſo well read in Diuinitie, as Hee is not onely a Prince to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but (for his learning) might be a Prieſt to enſtruct his people. Feare not then (oh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned France) but He hath taken your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe by the hand, not onely to leade Her to all happineſſe on earth, but to bring Her felicitie; For what aduiſe can She (who is ſo well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the dutie of a royall louing Spouſe) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, which diſtilleth like <hi>Nectar</hi> from his lips? Or what counſell ſhall proceed from Him, but that which tendeth to the welfare of her bodie, &amp; the ſauing of her ſoule &amp; body hereafter? Oh no, neuer was Princeſſe bleſt with a more holy, happie, heauenly Head, than She, in being vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Highneſſe; who, as Hee hath know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo He hath loue to direct Her to an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie end. Had his heart beene the harbourer of loue onely without knowledge, it had beene but as a blinde Guide; and knowledge, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loue to put it in practife, had been but as a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12264:22"/>fruitleſſe plant, or power without a will; but our mighty Prince, as He hath no ſmall meaſure of wiſdome, ſo He hath an infinite abundance of affection, affection ſo great, as indeed Hee is nothing but loue, loue to his God, loue to his Princeſſe, loue to his people; all of which are in Him ſo exceeding, that none of any of thoſe three particulars can be in any one perſon more eminent, than they bee ioyntly found in Him: For He loueth God aboue Himſelfe, Hee loueth Her as Himſelfe, becauſe She is halfe Himſelfe, and He loueth his People almoſt as Hee loueth Her. He loueth God, becauſe Hee is maried to Him myſtically; He loueth Her, as being knit vnto Him in mariage really; Hee loueth his People, as being wedded vnto them repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely indeed; He is ſo much loue, as none that liues but loues Him.</p>
            <p>The Lord of Heauen hath manifeſted his loue to Him in his mercie; for when Hee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke that dangerous voyage out of his Countrey, Great Brittaine, into Spaine, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in the iourney, dangerous in the end of it indeed, nothing but danger, both for his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage thither, his arriuall there, his departure from thence, being full of feare, and compoſed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12264:23"/>of nothing but danger; for the waues, being proud of ſuch a Burthen, did ſwell with ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the ſurges ſoared aboue the ſhip, as if the ſea had longed to haue her wombe the Tombe of ſuch a Worthie, and had intended to haue erected her honour vpon his ruine.</p>
            <p>But God, to whom the windes and the ſeas obey, did ſtill the rage of <hi>Neptune,</hi> and cloſed vp the mouth of <hi>Aeolus,</hi> in ſo much, as his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were all made fortunate in his happie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, reioycing that they had Him any waies, but more ioyous that they had Him ſingle; but now moſt exulting that He is vnited, by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bond of wedlocke, to your Princeſſe of France, and wee by that meanes conioyned to you. Thus hath the Lord, to the comfort of all well-diſpoſed people, deliuered our beſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Prince, and in bringing Him from Spaine, hath brought Him to France, that howſoeuer his loue began in the other, yet it might end in this; in which Hee hath giuen moſt infinite content vnto his Kingdomes, who diſtaſted the likelyhood of the former, as much as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the certaintie of this new Contract.</p>
            <p>Surely, God hath manifeſted his infinite loue and reſpect to our noble Prince, in ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12264:23"/>bleſſing his proper Selfe in Himſelfe, and his people in Him, in reſpect of his deliuerance. Yea, God and man, your Highneſſe and all the world, may ſee the happineſſe we conceiue of this Mariage, and hope for from this Contract: And what was the efficient cauſe of this? but the loue of God to his Highneſſe, thus worthily diſpoſed to the content and happineſſe of his people.</p>
            <p>Here was the loue of God manifeſtly and miraculouſly expreſt to Him and all this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in this one particular: but if I ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to make a whole diſcourſe of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as well towards his Bodie as his Soule, my taske would be as infinite as his bleſſings. But to leaue our mightie Prince, whoſe actions doe more commend Himſelfe, let France but as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceiue of our Nobles as they deſerue, and they ſhall finde a moſt ineffable cauſe of moſt vnſpeakable Ioy in this Confederation; for their breſts are the lodges of loyaltie. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, howſoeuer ſome of our naturall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men haue lifted vp vnnaturally their hands againſt their Leige &amp; Soueraigne, neuertheleſſe it was their religion, not their diſpoſition, which moued them to it. And how long time,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12264:24"/>hath our King reſted free from danger, begot and nurſt vp by his Nobles? No, ſuch, I dare ſay, is (or at leaſt ought to bee) their loue to their gracious King, that they deeme it more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to be his Seruant, than anies Soueraigne. For whereas generally great Kings weare Crownes like our Sauiours, made of thornes, compoſed of cares, which makes their eyes as Sentinels, to watch continually, leſt treaſon ſhould ſurprize and ouerthrow; and feares en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne the minde to keepe diligent watch, leſt treaſon ſhould euert both Perſon and people: their pettie Crownes are crowned with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, they are not affrighted with danger, neither doth feare make their night of reſt, a day of trauell vnto them; and all by their meanes, who like a ſtately Cedar to the adioyning trees, ſhelters them from tempeſts, and drops downe the honie of peace vpon them. This labour on his part begets the childe of loue in them, and they deeme no iniurie ſo great, nor apprehend any wrong ſo grieuous, as that which is done to their Prince: neither doe they coniecture any greater indignitie can bee done to them, than when He is not dignified; they count that glorie leſt which doth not redound to Him,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12264:24"/>and that honour to be as nothing, with which He is not graced; and therefore like ſo many pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, they doe ſupport Him vpon the ſhoulders of their obedience, who is their Roofe, their Couer &amp; Protector. To the grauer ſort of the which Nobilitie, our King ſtands as a Patterne for them to imitate, in ſoundneſſe of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, depth of learning, and other vertues: and to the younger, our Prince ſerues as a Tutor, to teach them, and inſtruct them what way leadeth to the perfection of honour and true glorie; and indeed none can bee more willing to ſet them an example, than He; and none more deſirous to follow ſuch a Leader, than they; they being proud in ſuch a Patterne, and Hee ioyfull in them.</p>
            <p>Oh who can meaſure the happineſſe of that Kingdome, where the Prince is ſo accompliſht in the parts of his bodie and endowments of minde? in whoſe actions all his followers may reade whole Lectures of Ethicks and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie; And thrice fortunate is that Prince, all whoſe Nobles ſtriue to be his pictures, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one deſireth and ſtriueth to haue neereſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, and to be drawne to the life, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his pourtraicture: each of them reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12264:25"/>to be the ſhadow of ſuch a ſubſtance, and to bee like the creature which is is ſo like the Creator.</p>
            <p>Here is no treaſon plotted, no inſurrections made by them, but all thoſe which doe truely feare &amp; loue God, doe truly feare &amp; loue their Soueraigne. Haply indeed, afore they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his vertues, and the light of his royall worth ſhined amongſt them, they might attempt ſome thing vnworthie of themſelues, nay baſe in the higheſt degree, as to be the death of Him which gaue life to ſo many, and with the pulling downe of the <hi>Primus Motor,</hi> ruine all the inferiour orbes of our Kingdome; but when they ſaw that his vertues made God his Friend, it was in vaine for them to bee his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; for all their treacherous attempts were but as ſowing the ſhoare, or waſhing a Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moore, labour in vaine.</p>
            <p>It is folly for <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when God bleſſeth him; and for them to ruine, when God preſerueth; in ſo much, as now his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment pleaſeth the Romiſh Catholiques, whom formerly their palates diſtaſted; and all our Nobles (if their bad conſciences doe not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe that title) doe honour Him, and beare a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12264:25"/>moſt affectionate reſpect to all his Poſteritie, eſpecially our royall Prince, whom all our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles labour in all their actions to pleaſe and imitate.</p>
            <p>Oh bleſſed Kingdome, where the Nobilitie doth ſo affect the Prince, and the Prince doth ſo much reſpect the Nobilite, and both of them are in loue with vertue; where the Peeres are ſo peereleſſe in their courteſie, loue to their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and loyaltie to their King; who are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more happie, than when they vndertake ſome enterpriſe for the happineſſe of both; who are not ſeruants to ſeruile feare, but Maſter-pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of valour; ſo that they are as much feared abroad, as fauoured and honoured at home: and how can they want honour, ſo long as our King and Prince, to whom true honour is due, honour them? Or haply, if they ſhould (as they neuer doe) neglect to reſpect them, yet then owne vertues would, in ſilence, ſpeake them worthie; who are ſo wiſely valiant, that they will not refuſe to hazard their liues, for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their Countrey; their eſtate, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of a limbe; nor the cutting off of a limbe, for the welfare of the whole bodie, who, though they can actiuely ſuffer prines, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12264:26"/>other dangers which would paſſiuely fall vpon them, yet they will not ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to any baſe kinde of miſerie. No ſurely, they know valour is vertue, and vertue hath euer more her limits: and therefore, as the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle preyeth not vpon flies, ſo they which are nobly bred, and haue their great birth ſeconded with good education, ſcorne to aime at at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuements of ſmall import; but ſhoot at high marks of great conſequence. Some of them valiantly defend the walls (as I may ſo terme them) of their Countrey, leſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies too neere approach, might make their Countrey too neere a ruine. Others, like <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> doe not ſticke to forſake their natiue ſoile; their wiues, their children, their lands and their poſſeſſions, to ſeeke for honour in a foraigne Countrey, and reſtore the wronged to their right; to reuenge a Prince, great in his vertues, though meane in his fortunes, his fortunes not ſo meane by birth, but by oppreſſion; oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Tyrant vſurping his Dominions; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, the which I cannot name, nay not ſo much as thinke on, but it forceth briniſh teares, forced and baniſht from a grieued heart, to ſee Religion ſo defaced, a Countrey ſo diſpeopled,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12264:26"/>the people ſo maſſacred and murdred. Then on, braue Brittaines Heroes, runne in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended courſe, and being prickt on with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, continue vntill you come to your iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies end; that ſo future ages may erect Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees to the eternall memories of your famous names, that children yet vnborne may ſay; Theſe were the Worthies, by whoſe meanes a deſolate Countrey was repeopled, a wronged Prince releeued, an oppreſſing Tyrant diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited. Conſider, oh yee truly ennobled, the cauſe of the war, the iuſtneſſe of the cauſe, the vertue of the Prince, the rare perfections of his Spouſe, the hopefulneſſe of their Iſſue, the neere affinitie they haue with your Soueraigne, being deriued and propagated from his loines; the conſanguinitie with your Prince: and ſurely, theſe motiues cannot chuſe but inflame you with courage, and accend your furie to make you fight valiantly, and conquer victoriouſly, the enemies of him, who is a fauourer and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of your true religion, a Sonne to your Soueraigne, a Brother to your Prince, a friend to you all.</p>
            <p>But alaſſe, what a needleſſe thing it is to caſt a drop into the Ocean? or to adde a ſparke
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12264:27"/>to the fierie region? My words are but as wind, to blow the fire which is ſufficiently kindled; for I, and all this Realme and Dominion with me, are verily and really perſwaded, that your valour is at ſo high a pitch, it cannot bee raiſed higher; ſuch be our Nobles, and therefore fit obiects for ſuch a Princeſſe, who thogh her ſex will not permit her to be an actor, yet her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minde doth incite her: and no doubt ſhee cannot chuſe but delight to ſee her Court com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of nothing but ſuch vndaunted and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Captaines, who though they bee moſt affable &amp; courteous in Court, yet they are moſt terrible &amp; couragious in combat. I doubt not, but it is a delectable ſpectacle to ſee your braue Martialliſts, as <hi>Caeſar, Pompey, Alexander,</hi> and ſuch like, though painted, &amp; that not vnto the life; for time hath waſted and worne out the true pictures of them. But in theſe your Nobles, moſt illuſtrious Princeſſe, you may ſee them all liuing: for if vertue can make one like, there is none ſuruiuing hath a neerer reſemblance to them, than your noble Seruants, and obſeruant Nobles haue of them. Is it the care of their Countrey, which wee ſhould make the ſubiect of our compariſon? the Publique good hath
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12264:27"/>beene reſpected of them, more than their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate commoditie; They know they are not borne to themſelues onely, but to the benefit of the place in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they haue had birth and being. This is their reſolution in generall, but giue me leaue: As the whole Kingdom is bound by du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and gratitude, to nominate ſome particulars, as he, who is the Fauourite of God, his King, Prince, and Countrey, the Duke of Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, who is not ſo ſtiled vnworthily, for hee doth truely deſerue it: Hath he not beene loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to our Soueraigne? And wheras other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, which haue beene (though neuer thus) aduanced, haue ſought to flie too high vpon the waxen wings of ambition, higher than either modeſtie or his Maieſtie permitted; hee neuer roſe higher than it pleaſed the King to lift him: ſo that he hath gained more honour by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie and vertue, than the King could giue him by his meanes; for goods may bee giuen by an earthly Soueraigne, but grace is an effect of a higher power, comming immediately from God; the King might preferre him, but it was God onely could make him humble in his performances, the which hee hath alwaies beene, ſhewing no leſſe loyall affection to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12264:28"/>King, than louing affection to his kinred. But looke into his loue which hee beareth to our Prince, and you ſhall finde him to be as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Ionathan</hi> vnto our righteous <hi>Dauid;</hi> in all his trauell and troubles, how conſtantly did he attend on Him, being almoſt as inſeparable an Adiunct to his Highneſſe, as heat to the fire, or light to the Sunne? being as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Nahomi,</hi> readie to goe whither ſoeuer He went. Neither did his perſon onely, but his care accompanie Him, watching continually leſt any treaſon might bee plotted againſt Him, leſt any trap might be laid to enſnare Him, leſt any ſubtill Serpents (as thoſe hot Countries are full of them) might ſting Him. It was hee that tooke the leaſt diſgrace done vnto the Prince, more heauily and hainouſly, than the greateſt indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie could be offered vnto himſelfe. It was he which diſcerned all the politique proceedings of Spaine; and it is hee (vnder God) to whom wee owe eternall gratitude, for the welfare of this our Kingdome, and the people are perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually bound for this their proſperitie: and I doubt not, but thoſe, who are not like Swine, (which eate the acornes vnder the tree, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer looke vp to the tree from whence they fall)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12264:28"/>doe moſt worthily acknowledge, and heartily affect that moſt Illuſtrious Duke, for his tender and zealous loue, both of his Princes ſafetie, and Countries good.</p>
            <p>Truth it ſelfe ſpeaketh it, and therefore who but the enemies of Truth can oppoſe it? that promotion neither commeth from the Eaſt, nor the Weſt, but onely from the Lord. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the hearts of Kings are in the hands of God, to turne them at his pleaſure: and it is as farre from doubt, as Heauen from Hell, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed our King hath honoured you, but it was by Gods appointment; He hath preferred you, but it was by Gods directions, and God dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Him to aduance you, that you might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit this Countrey, in being an Inſtrument, to finde out the intendments of Spaine, as alſo to further this bleſſed Contract with France; and I dare ſay, or (if my word may not be taken) I can produce millions of witneſſes, to teſtifie and depoſe, that the gaping earth, after a long parching drought, did neuer more acceptably entertaine a liuely ſhowre, than the Brittiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this Vnion. Neither was euer the dew of <hi>Hermon,</hi> diſtilling vpon the Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> more welcome to it, than this happie and hopefull
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12264:29"/>Coniunction to vs. Neither let me omit to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in the behalfe of our Countrey-men, all poſſible thanks to my Noble Lord of Donca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who hath ſo well and worthily behaued, and carried himſelfe, in the effecting of this bleſſed Confederation, as in making this Match, and effecting this Contract, hee hath robbed multitudes of their ſoules, and won the hearts of all the people; for ſhould hee liue neuer ſo long, and all his life time ſtudie, and euer ſtudie effectually, and all his ſtudies ſhould be wholly to benefit his Countrey, hee could neuer haue excogitated a meanes more likely, to bring whole ſhowres of all kinde of Bleſſings vpon theſe Kingdomes, than this, whereby England is ioyned to France, and France to England; the moſt fertile Countries of the world are ioyned together, with the kiſſes of peace and amitie. To you therfore, moſt Noble Lord, as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit by which meanes God hath conueyed this happines, we preſent our well wiſhes. For who is it, but you, moſt Honoured Lord, to whom we are more indebted, than to your care, for the finiſhing of this Vnion? It was the eyes of your Indgement, which foreſaw what proſperitie it would bring to the Prince, and what happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12264:29"/>it would bring to England, to haue (her Lyons adorned with Frances Lillies, and the Flower-Deluce and the Roſe bound vp, and conioyned. What bed ſo ſweet, as that which is compoſed of Lillies and Roſes? What kiſſes more delightfull, than when they are linked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? And what Contract could haue been more conſolatorie, than this of France and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? To you therfore, Great Britaine ſendeth the beſt of her wiſhes, to attend you, and moſt powerfull prayers to guard you, and preſerue you from all perils, that you may liue to doe God glorie, and your Countrey good, in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming many profitable offices vnto it.</p>
            <p>Here then, if it pleaſe France and this moſt Royall Ladie, to take but a ſuruey of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable excellencie of the Peeres and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, by whom She ſhall bee attended in Great Btittaine, Shee ſhall happily, and to her great comfort and content, vnderſtand, that She ſhall ſhine like <hi>Phoebe</hi> in this our Orbe, enuironed round about with theſe glorious ſtarres and reſplendent lights, the Nobles of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>But to the end they may conceiue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of their happineſſe, <hi>Capape</hi> (as I may ſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12264:30"/>ſay) and weigh but the worth of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and vulgar ſort of people, in this our Iland, it will ſoone, appeare, that euen in the loweſt ſort of people, they ſhall finde higheſt degrees of happineſſe: Firſt, in regard of the mutuall affection which is likely to be between Her and our Nation, whether it bee for ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of bloud, or aequiparancie of conditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he ſaw the two Iewes at diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one with another, hee could excogitate no meanes more forcible to moue them to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement, than reducing their affinitie to their remembrance, telling them they were bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then: then ſurely, ought there not to be great affection betweene the two famous Nations of the Brittiſh and the French, ſince there is ſo much affinitie? Yes ſurely; and to the end that there may bee (as there ought to bee) eternall concord, let vs remember we are brethren, and of the ſame bloud.</p>
            <p>For there be verie few in England, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly from their Fathers and Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, or indirectly by ſome contract, haue not ſome of the French bloud lodged in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes. And if we examine the diſpoſitions of either Nation, wee ſhall finde them not like
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12264:30"/>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> or <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> of oppoſite qualities; but wee ſhall ſee an abſolute agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betweene them, in their vertuous incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and conditions.</p>
            <p>Doe we ſeeke for valour? who of more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect proweſſe, than the French and the Engliſh? Who haue been ſo often Combatants and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, both for their Countrey and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as France and England?</p>
            <p>The French are true-hearted, neuer carrying two faces vnder one hood; but deeming it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cowardice, than true valour, to ouercome by deceit and policie, for the moſt part carrying their hearts at their tongues-end; and though they ſpeake not euerie thing which they know, yet they ſpeake nothing with their tongues, but that which they thinke in their hearts.</p>
            <p>Our Engliſh are not deceitfull and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, cooling their pottage and warming their hands with the ſame breath; but their ſpeeches are the mirrours of their mindes, in which you may ſee their intentions, and by their words you may attaine to the ſcience of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>The French are vpright and iuſt, deeming it the loſſe of their worth not to keep their word,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12264:31"/>and the moſt baſe ſeruility not to be their words Maſters, ſcorning fraud and truce-breaking, not ſeeking to ruſh vpon another mans poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or to encroach vpon others Dominions.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh are performers of that which they promiſe, prouing the truth of their words by the triall of their deeds, accounting it a deep wound to their reputation, not to performe their promiſes; and that the lie deſerues (more than is in the Prouerbe) not onely a ſtab, but damnation; they are content with that which the Lord hath allotted to them, and doe not ſo much ſeeke to offend their neighbours, as to defend themſelues.</p>
            <p>In a word: Are the French affable, ſober, wiſe, modeſt, temperate, pious, prudent, coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, conſtant, magnanimous, mercifull, iuſt? The Engliſh doe anſwer them in all theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie qualities, and are full of courteſie in their carriage, of ſobrietie in their countenances, of modeſtie in their behauiours, of temperance in their diets, of pietie in their religion, of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in their practiſes, of courage in their combats and controuerſies, of conſtancie and ſtayedneſſe in their affections, of magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in their enterpriſes, of mercie in pardoning
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12264:31"/>thoſe offences which may poſſibly be forgiuen, and of Iuſtice in puniſhing thoſe offences, which may not be permitted.</p>
            <p>Therefore of a certaintie, no earthly bleſſing is able to counteruaile your happineſſe, whoſe Princeſſe is combined and conioyned with our Prince; whoſe people is ſo worthie, that Hee doth not ſeeme like a Royall Golden Pillar built vpon a Baſe of Lead, but a worthie Prince ſet ouer a worthie people. Happie therefore is France in her companie, happie the Princeſſe in her command: They extraordinarily fortunate, that they ſhall haue commerce with a Nation, who will not be to them as a ſtrange people, of a differing diſpoſition; but will bee of a corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencie of condition with them: and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie She, that ſhall haue ſuch ſubiects, ſo wiſe, ſo worthie, ſo iuſt, ſo honeſt, that Shee may well thinke this her Kingdome, to be a little Heauen, in which She ſits as Queene, and her Subiects as ſo many Saints.</p>
            <p>Neither doe the ſweet-pleaſing ſtreames of ioy and ſolace, flow onely to France from this fountaine; but as the ſtomacke, though it bee the proper reſident place and receptacle of the meat, yet doth not only feed and ſatisfie it ſelfe;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12264:32"/>but likewiſe doth nouriſh and content all the parts about it; ſo this bleſſed Vnion, and ſweet Coniunction, doth not onely benefit the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Countries, betweene whom it is made; but doth likewiſe reioyce the neighboring Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the reſt of the League &amp; Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Caſt but an eye vpon Venice, and there, euen of one halfe blinde, may bee diſcerned, how all in generall applaud and laud it, infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reioycing, that their Friends and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates ſhould be ſo fortunate; that England and France ſhould bee ſo ioyned together, in the knot of true loue and amitie. From this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractariſeth a hope of the vanquiſhing of their foes, and that by this meanes a happie ſucceſſe ſhall accompany all their iuſt enterpriſes againſt their enemies: alſo, being mounted vpon the wings of glorie, they ſhall bee ſeated vpon the necks of their ſubdued aduerſaries; and that ſuch conqueſts ſhall follow this Contract, and ſuch victories theſe Nuptialls, and the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of men now liuing, and ſucceeding ages, ſhall ſee and ſay, It was the mariage of the mightie Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Ladie <hi>Henrette Maria,</hi> which were the Parents and Producers of Religions comfort, of the reſtoring of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12264:32"/>wronged to their right; for God, or the verie day, in which <hi>Hymens</hi> Rites were ſolemnized betweene Them, did matchall good people to happineſſe, crowned Them with victorie, to the conſolation of all true Chriſtian Princes, friends to equitie, enemies of ambition, fauourers and followers of vertue.</p>
            <p>But if our intelligence trauell a little lower, and you make recourſe into the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, no tongue is able to vtter what they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, nor any pen almoſt to write the ioyous ſpeeches they vtter, for the confirmation of this Contract, than which nothing could haue been more deſired, no newes better accepted: And whereas the ſpeeches of the former Match did ſeeme vnto them as hideous as Hell, and as ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as Thunder, this is a lightning vnto their hearts; for now in ſtead of feares, they haue friends on all ſides, Allies and Confederates, which are of will and power to aſſiſt them, and to make reſiſtance againſt their enemies. The former Match did ſeeme vnto them as a ſtorme of warre, threatning to demoliſh the Architect of their welfare; this, as a Calme of peace, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing ſecuritie to their proſperitie. Oh happie Brittaine! in ſuch a bleſſed Prince, who is by ſo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12264:33"/>much more fortunate, by how much more He is a meanes to make others happie; and from whom can more happineſſe bee deriued, than from our Prince? who cloathes ſo many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes at his Mariage-day, in robes of comfort, and giues to ſo many Common-wealths ſuch great fauours, as neuer did any Potentate in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, nor is likely to doe in following time: who hath lifted out of the mire of miſerie, ſo many drooping hearts and diſcontented ſoules. Indeed, neuer was Mariage more hopefull than this of theſe two moſt hopefull Princes, by the coniunction of which two propitious Planets, in this our firmament of Chriſtendom, it preſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the ſweet diſtillation of the drops of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, vpon ſo many, eſpecially the Low-Countries, whoſe Inhabitants are filled with heaped meaſure of mirth, for this conſolatorie, moſt ioyfull, and happie Coniunction. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Graue as well naturally as nominally, as well really as titularly, who is not onely graue and to bee honoured for his yeeres, but graue and to be imitated for his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, being not onely adorned with the graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his head, but with the grace of his heart, doth heartily praiſe the God of Heauen, by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12264:33"/>whom all marriages, eſpecially of Princes, bee made, for conſtituting and appointing this Contract, and croſſing that which was preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Spaine; For that had laid his breſt open to his enemies, it had beene a way which had led to the waſting of his Countrey; had it proceeded, he might haue ſaluted it, and ſaid, as <hi>Ahab</hi> ſpoke to <hi>Eliah, Haſt thou found me, ob mine enemie?</hi> But hee may welcome this with the ſpeech of <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Ahiah, He is a good man, and bringeth glad tydings.</hi> Neither can it miniſter any ſmall ioy to the moſt illuſtrious, Sonne of our moſt gracious Soueraigne, the King of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, who hath along time beene rackt vpon the racke of hard misfortunes, and endured the grimme looks of aduerſitie; but now he hopes ſafely to ſaile in the Ocean of pleaſure, and to ſee the ſmiling countenance of Ioy and Solace. He doubteth not, but now his noble affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Father, is not onely powerfull in his owne proper forces, but ſtrong in Alliance, with that mightie potent French King, who both of them being ſo puiſſant in meanes, men, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and munition, ſo ſufficiently stored with wiſe graue Counſellours to aduiſe, with young able men to act, and put their counſell in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12264:34"/>They will ioyne forces to reioyne his detained Diadem to his head, and to reſtore Him to his Countrey and Dignitie.</p>
            <p>This was the day likewiſe, which the onely Siſter of our proſperous mightie Prince, and Daughter of the Imperiall Maieſtie of our mightie Soueraigne, ſo long looked for, and ſo much longed for, in which Shee might haue a Siſter by mariage, though not by birth, with whom She might make a mutuall exchange of intire affection, that She might finde one true friend, that might bee her Siſter, both in deed and vertue; that hauing found one ſo neere Herſelfe, ſo like Herſelfe, her ioy might euen almoſt exceed Herſelfe; and who more fit to be Siſters, than thoſe who are ſo concording in vertuous conditions; the leaſt of whoſe rare exquiſite perfections cannot bee imitated by any, but by one another; for who ſo modeſt, ſo bountifull, ſo beautifull, ſo chaſte, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, ſo wiſe, and euerie waies ſo worthie, as <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but <hi>Henrette Maria?</hi> all that they differ is in that which notwithſtanding in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Them is a vertue; for the one is a chaſte Matron, the other a pure Virgin; the one the Mother, as well of many children, as of many
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12264:34"/>holy deeds; the other, the mother onely of vertuous actions. The Almightie of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie grant, that as Shee is her perfect Patterne in the one, ſo Shee may truely reſemble Her, that ſo Shee may bee the happie Mother of many children, and Hee the fortunate Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Progenitour of many Princes, that Shee being like a fruitfull Vine vpon the wall-ſide, his children may bee like Oliue Branches round about his table; and that in his Poſteritie, not onely his Highneſſe, but all the world may bee happie; ſo alſo the Pfaltz-graues Princely Babes and hopefull Iſſue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, in regard all their Friends are not likely to deceaſe with their Parents, but that from their mightie Vncle Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his loynes, ſhall ſpring ſuch Princely Sprigs, who will take their parts againſt all thoſe, which with an enuious eye and a malicious minde behold their perſons. For euer therefore let this Contract bee chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled in the Regiſter of Fame, which hath thus impoſed an Epilogue to the dolefull Tragedie, ſo paſſionately acted in the boſomes of the Royll King and Queene of Bohemia, and hath begun a Prologue to a ioyfull Comedie, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of which ſhall bee warre and bloudie
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12264:35"/>diſſention, but the laſt act containeth the peace of the Church, the releefe of the oppreſſed, the ruine of Antichriſt, and the aduancement of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Thus from theſe two moſt excellent Princes, ſpring tides of happineſſe, ouerflowing many Countries; and good fortune, of which they are the Authours, crownes many forraigne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but moſt eſpecially this our Iland, and all his Maieſties of Great Brittaines Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>For if wee ſhall but behold France with the eye of mature iudgement, wee ſhall finde it ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with all kinde of commodities fit for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and traffique, being (as it were) Gods garden, in which Hee had planted all his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and benefits; for what rare bleſſing is it not richly furniſhed with? as corne, cattell, fiſh, fowle, and all manner of fruit, either plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the eye, or delightfull to the taſte? whoſe ſoyle is cloathed in a greene mantle, dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and adorned with all kinde of various, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable, ſenſe-delighting, odoriferous flowers. Indeed no Kingdomes ſoyle hath more beautie and bountie than France, no Countrey better ſituated, more abounding with excellent wits,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12264:35"/>both in the time of warre and peace, than France: there is no Kingdome eſtabliſhed with godlier Lawes, no Monarchie more mightie, of authoritie more abſolute Soueraigne, being a Kingdome ſo well fortified with power, and so well qualified with pietie: Indeed, neuer was the foundation of any Empire laid with more wiſdome; and being built, vpheld, and the ruines repaired with more diſcretion than France. Doe you inquire after the greatneſſe of her Prouinces? They are like ſo many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, yet all vnited in one Neuer were there any Soueraignes of any Kingdomes, which haue more conſtantly laboured for the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpell, and the planting of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, than the French Kings, who haue made cleane the floore of Chriſten dome, ſwept away ſo much filthineſſe, and diuerted that great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Infidels, which threatned ſhipwracke to the French Nation; from whence they haue their deſerued titles of moſt Chriſtian Kings. What worthie men, yea and moſt excellent Kings, hath France produced? of whom wee may truely report, that they were moſt valiant in warre, moſt wiſe in counſell, carrying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues not inſultingly in their proſperitie, nor
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12264:36"/>yet deiectedly in their aduerſitie; but being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt conquered in ſhew, they became Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours in effect; and when they were moſt in deſpaire, yet neuer deſpaired of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale; who, as they manifeſted great loue to their ſubiects, ſo their ſubiects expreſſed great loue and affection to them.</p>
            <p>Doe you ſearch who were the Anceſtours of the French, and inquire after the originall of that Nation, you ſhall finde them neither in the ruines and aſhes of Troy, neither in the Fens of Moolides, but were principally deſcended from them in Germany, a Nation mighty in ſtrength and valour, who by defending themſelues, and ſuccouring others, came to be a people power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Armes, who ſtill maintained their liberty with their ſword, from whence they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the other Germanes <hi>Fraunce,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies free, or reiecting ſeruitude and bondage.</p>
            <p>And it may bee ſpoken truely and without flatterie, that neuer Kingdome might better boaſt of ſo many worthie Princes as this may; As <hi>Pharamond,</hi> the firſt Layer of the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Monarchie; <hi>Clodion</hi> his Succeſſour in this building; <hi>Meroued</hi> the Continuer, and Augmenter of the Edifice; <hi>Clouis,</hi> whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12264:36"/>is to bee reuerenced of all poſteritie, and whoſe worthie deeds are to bee had in an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting remembrance, as being the firſt that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Chriſtian religion to others conqueſts, and adorned that rare foundation with the faith of Chriſt, the primeſt ornament of any Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, by which meanes the hearts of the Gaules (who for the moſt part embraced the Goſpell) were as much vnited to him by fauour, as his was to God by faith; who by this meanes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from them voluntarie obedience, and was made aſſured poſſeſſour of the others vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, who likewiſe receiued the name of his new Dominions, and were called by the name of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To omit that renowned Prince, <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maigne</hi> who being inriched with ſingular gifts, both of bodie and minde, repaired the ruine of the Empire, &amp; was confirmed King of France, and Emperour of Rome, to the great aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Religion, and comfort of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; whoſe iſſue, although it did not alwaies inherit, either their Fathers valour or his honour; yet God, who though He may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the perſons, yet ſtill guardeth and guideth the ſtate of Monarchies, did raiſe vp a worthie
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12264:37"/>Succeſſour of that Race, to wit, <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> a Prince adorned both with wiſdome and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, ioyning wholſome Lawes to his force of armes, and well-gouerned equitie to his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, did ſo ouercaſt this erected Kingdome with ſuch, both godly and goodly Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as it withſtood the ſtormes of many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ages.</p>
            <p>And of late yeeres, <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, the prime Prince of the bloud, and firſt King of the Royall Race of <hi>Burbon,</hi> a Prince endowed with all gifts and rare qualities, requiſite for the reſtoring of a Kingdoms ſicke and languiſhing eſtate, to the former health and happineſſe: who ſucceeding <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, the laſt of the Royall Race of <hi>Valois,</hi> who was ſlaine by a Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobine, in the Crowne and Dignitie of a King, found the Kingdome peſtered with ſo many peſtilent euils, which was like a bodie ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and weakned with all kinde of diuerſitie of diſeaſes, ſurcharged with melancholy, and diuers other bad humours, which did ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for predominancie, as it was full of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine broyles and ciuill diſſentions, the which being fed with choller of the people, did daily threaten the ouerthrow and deſtruction of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12264:37"/>whole Continent, if God had not in time ſent that good Phyſitian, <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, whoſe might and mildneſſe compoſed ſuch whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome medicines and rare remedies, for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of his Kingdomes welfare, that by his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour hee encountred his enemies, and reduced his diſtracted and almoſt deſtroyed ſubiects, to their dutifull obedience; in ſo much; as his moſt gracious gouernment was likely to haue brought that Kingdome to a moſt peaceable and proſperous eſtate, if a curſed cruell murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer had not impoſed an vntimely end by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate ſtab to his life, and by conſequence to his gouernment, with whoſe life the preſent proſperitie of the Kingdome was ended, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard He left none to weild his Scepter, but his Sonne, then Daulphine, now King, <hi>Lewis,</hi> whoſe tender yeeres, though they promiſed much, yet they could performe verie little in the ruling of ſuch a mightie Nation: But God, who is euermore a Father of the fatherleſſe, and a Husband to the Widow, became a mightie Protectour of this fatherleſſe Countrey, ſtill preſeruing it from all perills, guarding the Daulphine from all dangers, till at length, Hee attaining to the ripeneſſe of yeeres and vertues,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12264:38"/>was fit to bee the Gouernour of ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; in ſo much, as now it may bee truely ſtiled, The moſt flouriſhing and fortunate Common-wealth in Chriſtendome: Then what better or fitter amitie, than betweene Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and People ſo faithfull, and two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſo fruitfull, as France and Brittaine? What greater likelyhood can there be of loue, than between men ſo like in qualities, as the French and Engliſh, and two Countries ſo rich as France and England?</p>
            <p>It is an ancient approued Maxime in Philoſophie. <hi>Simile ſimili gaudet,</hi> The like reioyceth in the like; and it is as receiued an axiom in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, <hi>Amicitia debet eſſe inter aequales:</hi> For if a rich man be in the bond of friendſhip with a poore man, their loue is not likely to bee of any long continuance; for the want of the one will wearie the good will of the other, and like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> kine, the leane ones will eat vp the fat.</p>
            <p>But when two fertile Kingdome, which are the Palaces of <hi>Ceres,</hi> and Temples of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> ſhall ioyne together, it is not onely likely to bee great for the quantitie, but durable for the time, when as they ſhall not onely haue the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12264:38"/>of peace, but alſo of plentie, when as neither of them ſhall impoueriſh, but both of them ioyntly enrich each other.</p>
            <p>This is the ioy of our moſt mightie, wiſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uict Monarch, King <hi>Iames,</hi> who is as well the father of his Countrey England, as of his Sonne Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> who cannot chuſe but reioyce to ſee his Countrey ſo well matched to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſo commodious and profitable. There is no father but deſireth and ioyeth to ſee his daughter wealthily beſtowed vpon one of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall worth and meanes; then well may his Royall Perſon reioyce at this Mariage of his Kingdom, which hath found a Mate ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo plentifull, ſo abounding with all riches, ſo enriched with all benefits, as France.</p>
            <p>Doth He deſire peace? it is able in the time of peace to ſend Him rich commodities out of her ſtore-houſe. Doth He deſire warre? what is wanting there to maintaine it? It is populous for men, powerfull for money, plentifull for prouiſion; there are men to bee procured for money, money for men, &amp; ſuſtenance to be had for money, that nothing might be wanting, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the vpholding, for the beginning or continuance of a iuſt warre: Then how is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12264:39"/>England for euer obliged to the Almightie, who hath thus directed our King, thus affected our Prince to chuſe and ſelect ſo bleſſed a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, in ſo happie a Countrey, which is the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Mother of ſuch excellent wits, which is the Continent of ſuch affable, debonaire, and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous people, a rich Fountaine From whence all neceſſarie benefits flow to neighbouring Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which wanteth neither a fat fruitfull ſoyle to yeeld increaſe, nor laborious, painfull, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious men to till it, which hath beene the ſeat of ſo many mightie, wiſe, valiant, vnconquered Monarchs.</p>
            <p>Oh happie Brittaine! which though thou wert moſt happie in thy ſelfe, yet (if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) art more than moſt happie in ſuch a Siſter, which is the Palace of pleaſure, &amp; the Manſion-place of delight, which ſendeth all rare deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, as gifts vnto thy People; and the rareſt Gemme of Nature, the moſt exquiſite Fruit that euer that Countrey could make it ſelfe or other Countries happie in, The Ladie <hi>Henrette Maria,</hi> to thy Prince, whoſe vertues ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the life, more to the eyes of all, than the moſt perfect eloquence is able to declare them to the eares of any; who, in her virginitie,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12264:39"/>was wedded to Vertue, and is now marched with the moſt vertuous Prince that euer liued; who for vertue, parentage, education, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and portion, ſtands as a matchleſſe Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to all her ſex, and no whit vnworthie of ſuch a Husband.</p>
            <p>Conſider but her vertues, and you will ſay, and yet ſpeake nothing but that which you thinke, that Shee is rather an Angell ſent from Heauen, for to bee a Miracle and Oracle of her time, for all to admire, than borne of mortall ſeed, for any to imitate; in whom wiſdome ſits in her perfection, and all to make Her perfect, whoſe words are all weighed in the balance of conſideration in her minde, afore they be vented by her lips; for Shee knowes words are like time, once paſt, they cannot be recalled, and howſoeuer the tongue bee an vnruly euill, and that euill moſt predominant in a woman; yet Shee deeming it moſt vnworthie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand others, and not to command Her ſelfe, alwaies premeditating of whom, to whom, where and what She ſpeakes; and as Shee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers not her tongue to be the key of her mindes cloſet, where ſilence is a vertue; ſo Shee will not neglect to let her tongue bee the teſtament
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12264:40"/>of her minde, where neceſſitie enforceth Thrice happie Kingdome at this inſtant, in which there is ſuch a Princeſſe extant, ſo fully accompliſht with ſuch rare vertuous qualities: It is She, whoſe chaſtitie doth challenge the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie of all her Anceſtours, and ſtands as a Patterne to future ages, whoſe heart neuer har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured the leaſt thought of vncleanneſſe, whoſe Iuorie Alablaſter Soule hath not beene toucht or tainted with the leaſt impuritie can be imagined; but, from her infancie, hath been the vndefiled Temple of <hi>Diana;</hi> whoſe harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe heart hath euermore walked cloathed in a white ſpotleſſe robe of matchleſſe innocence, and hath beene hurtfull to none, except it hath beene in being too mercifull; and if She hath done any iniurie, it hath beene in doing good to thoſe which neuer deſerued it: Shee is free from the oppreſſion of the fatherleſſe, or wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the widow, free from the effuſion and pouring out of innocent bloud; her hands were neuer imbrued in the purple die of infants gore. And thus being guarded with the armour of proofe of innocence, She walkes ſecure, dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of danger; for neither doe needleſſe feares in the time of her watching, ſurprize Her; nor
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12264:40"/>horrid dreames of danger, in her ſleepe, affright Her; for her innocence doth euermore ſecure Her.</p>
            <p>Neither may her patience bee paſſed ouer in ſilence, who heiring her Father in his ſpirit (as if Hee had left Her his good <hi>Genius,</hi> as part of her Dowrie) is reſolute beyond her ſex, in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring aduerſities; and all afflictions, which time in the whole courſe of her life hath inflicted vpon Her, haue beene entertained like ſnow vpon the ground, without any noyſe or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring; Religion and Diſcretion did informe Her, that the more patiently She tooke her pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of her Heauenly Father, the more gently He would correct Her; and She deemes it meere madneſſe, with the fiſh, to leape out of the pan of miſerie, into the fire of impatience; or to ſeeke to withſtand that which She could not auoid: therefore in all thoſe ſickneſſes and afflictions, which God either for triall, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, hath inflicted vpon Her, Shee hath beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Herſelfe with ſuch meekneſſe, ſuch mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and yet ſuch courage of Spirit, as we may truely ſay, Shee hath beene Gods Patient in all her miſeries: if She were ſicke in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, yet her comfort was, Shee could not bee
<pb facs="tcp:12264:41"/>ſicker: and thus, though potions could not helpe her bodie, yet patience did cure her ſoule, and (like a rare extraordinarie Bird) She ſung in a ſtormie tempeſt, being not onely thankfull and praiſing God for his bleſſings on the right hand, but her afflictions on the left, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming all her croſſes with ſuch ſweet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements, as they had not the heart to ſtay long with ſuch a friend, that gaue them ſuch kinde entertainment, and good welcome.</p>
            <p>Neither may her humilitie be forgotten, who makes it Gentleman-Vſher for her Honour, eſteeming that honour cannot follow except humilitie goes afore; She knowes it is the Baſis vpon which all other vertues are erected, and that pride is a great diſgrace, euen in the greateſt Potentates: To ſee a poore deiected miſerable man, which is low and caſt downe in eſtate, low in minde, it is no wonder; but to ſee one high in honours and preferment, humble in ſpirit, it is a ſtrange raritie: And it is moſt true, that as there is nothing more odious in the ſight of God, than a poore man proud; ſo there is no ſight more acceptable to his All-ſeeing Eye, than to ſee one which is mightie, meane in his owne opinion: But ſuch is this honoured, yet
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12264:41"/>humble Ladie, who though She be laden with honours, riches, and vertues, yet like a fertile Plant, by how much more it is inriched with fruit, by ſo much neerer it bowes to the ground: So this Illuſtrious Princeſſe, by how much more God hath aduanced Her to dignities, by ſo much more Shee doth honour Him by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie.</p>
            <p>And to the end that Shee might walke ſafely betweene two extremes, and abſolutely attaine to the golden meane; as Shee is not prone to pride, ſo She is void of baſeneſſe; She doth not altogether forget the greatneſſe of her birth, but through the remembrance of it, is incited to goodneſſe of life; Shee holds it the higheſt indignitie, and the greateſt vnworthineſſe that may be, to be ſuperiour to any in birth or place, and to be inferiour to them in grace and vertue. And thus ſtriuing to exceed, Shee is beyond compare, and good in the ſuperlatiue, the which (howſoeuer Herſelfe doth more looke on the defects in her labouring to mend them, than thoſe perfections which cannot bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, whiles her diuine ſoule is ſhadowed with this veile of mortalitie, and depriued of the freedome in this priſon of fleſh) yet Shee
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12264:42"/>would haue others ſee her vertues, not in a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh vaine-glorie, but a religious pietie, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by her good example might bee the more ſtirred to the practiſe of vertuous actions, and that men ſeeing her good works, might glorifie her Father which is in Heauen, and as She doth holily deſire that they might ſee her vertuous diſpoſition and pious qualities, ſo Shee doth wiſely labour to couer her infirmities, and to burie in obliuion her (if there bee any in Her) imperfections. She conſiders Shee is ſet vpon a hill, and hath many eyes vpon Her, and that which is but a moat in anothers eye, is a beame in hers; that infirmitie which is but a ſcratch to anothers credit, is a wound to her reputation; She obſerues alſo, that as her weakneſſes are eminent, ſo they are dangerous: For if the King holds his necke awry, all the Subiects will imitate Him; if the Tutour ſtammers, the Scholler will ſcarce ſpeake plaine, and vulgar people thinke it their greateſt perfection to imitate their Prince, although it be in their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections; Shee therefore, to preuent that which might bee anywayes preiudiciall to her vnderlings, endeuours to be as perfect as may bee, and to hide that in which Shee is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.
<pb facs="tcp:12264:42"/>But that I may be conſtant in her prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, let me likewiſe commend her conſtancie; for whereas other women are like the Moone, euer changing, and in one inſtant loathing that which they loued, hauing the eyes of their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not fixed vpon one certaine obiect, but hauing their mindes drunke with the varietie of affections, they reele here and there, and their heads being ſicke of the ſtaggers of inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, they are indeterminate in all their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Shee, on the contrarie, being ſober and ſtayd in her fancie, loueth onely One, and will neuer leaue to loue Him: Light ſubſtances, as feathers, ſhittle-cocks, and ſuch like, are moued with euerie puffe, or the leaſt blaſt of winde; but creatures more ponderous and precious, as your Diamond, Rubie, Carbuncle, and Saphyr, are not remoued out of the place where they reſt, but by violence; and howſoeuer they bee harder to find, yet it is not ſo eaſie to loſe them. Some women doe loue <hi>ad libitum,</hi> and can finde no center of their deſires; but, like your ſtraw, are ſo accendible, as the leaſt puffe will ſet their affections on flaming, and kindle their deſires; but alas, as they are ſoone in, ſo they are ſoone out: It is an eaſie matter, in euerie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12264:43"/>place, to meet with ſuch light ſtuffe, but it is difficult to finde Diamonds, whoſe affections are well balanced, and whoſe fancies are of long continuance: But ſuch is this Princeſſe, ſo ſtayd, ſo ſober, ſo conſtant, ſo <hi>Penelope</hi>-like, whom many may wooe, but none can winne from <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> who though She may haue many pleaders for Her, yet non-ſuites them all but One; being ſo diuine a Creature, as in her affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Shee reſembleth her Creatour; who, whom He loueth, He loueth to the end. The beames of her loue, as they bee moſt bright, ſo they are of long continuance, being no wayes wauering, nor ſpeedily fading, but conſtant and durable. Neither is Shee conſtant in her affections onely, but alſo in her vertuous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for what vertue more naturall or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie in a Prince, than liberalitie? and who more liberall than Shee? Her bountie, like the Sunne, ſhines vpon all She ſees; She knoweth none are more miſerable, than they which are miſerably couetous, who ſtarue in a Cookes ſhop, pine in the midſt of plentie, who, <hi>Tantalus</hi>-like, haue golden apples aboue, and Cryſtall Fountaines beneath his chin; but yet, can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taſte the apples, to ſatisfie his hunger, nor
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12264:43"/>touch the water, to allay his thirſt. She there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, holding it a thing inconuenient, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand others, and not to command her paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and her purſe; Shee therefore eſteeming ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but the exiles of Fortune, the which Shee can keepe no longer, becauſe Shee muſt part from them, doth liberally and freely giue to ſuch, whoſe either earneſt petitions, or ſilent deſerts, doe plead for them: For reaſon teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Her, that they are giuen Her onely to giue to others; therefore, with moſt incomparable bountie, and yet diſcretion, Shee doth beſtow them; and like the Heauens, being full, Shee powreth and ſhowreth downe the dew of her pitie, vpon the gaping neceſſitie of poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: She well remembreth, that the faithfulleſt friends She can make, are her charitable deeds; for her goods leaue Her at her death, nothing we brought, and nothing we muſt carrie away: Her Friends and Allies forſake Her at her graue, they may accompanie Her to her tombe, but they will not dwell with her in darkneſſe; but her almeſdeeds and pious actions follow Her, ſaying vnto her ſoule, as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Nahomi, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoeuer thou goeſt, Ile follow thee.</hi> It is that which moues Her to ſhew ſuch pietie in her
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12264:44"/>pitie, that makes Her a Prop to the poore, a Staffe to the needie: It is from hence, that the bleſſings of the Lord doe ſtill accompanie Her, She is ſo much fauoured of Him, becauſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is ſo much fauoured in Her; and it is as far from doubt, as truth from falſhood, that Shee ſhall be the moſt fortunate, moſt bliſſefull and happie Princeſſe, that euer was extant in this Chriſtian world.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you ſeene her vertues in ſome part deciphered, though not to the full deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; for that were as impoſſible to containe her praiſes (who, though Shee bee young in yeeres, yet is old in Grace) in this ſmall volume, as to confine the boundleſſe Ocean to a ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne.</p>
            <p>But becauſe howſoeuer Vertue is true Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, yet Nobilitie is an ornament to Vertue; examine but her Princely Parentage, which is lineally deſcended from ſo many Kings and Emperours, neuer was Branch ſprung from a more Regall, Imperiall, and Royall Stocke, than She; therefore not to make any troubleſome ſearch into ancient Chronicles, but to looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe later moderne times, it will appeare, that neuer had childe greater cauſe to ioy in a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12264:44"/>father, than this Princeſſe in hers, whoſe Father <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, of the royall Race of Burbon, a Prince ſo truely, fully, and nobly accompliſht, as Hee deſerueth to bee ſtiled the Worthieſt of the French Monarchie; for finding the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome fraught with hatred, rebellion, infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, treaſon, and ſuch like; but Hee, by his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and diſcreet gouernment, like a wiſe Husband-man of that his vineyard, rooted out thoſe enormious weeds, planting in ſtead of them, loue to his Perſon, ſubmiſſion to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie, faithfulneſſe to his Crowne, and loyaltie to his Gouernment; and howſoeuer ſome did ſo farre oppoſe Him, as they ſought to depoſe Him, yet He being directed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by a Higher Power, in ſpight of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane violent oppoſitions, did triumph, both ouer domeſtique &amp; forraigne foes, and France may confeſſe truely, and without flatterie, that ſhe languiſhed with the want of ſuch a Prince, vntill He, like another <hi>Hercules,</hi> did ruine and root out thoſe hideous monſters, which did ſeeme prodigious to her owne proper proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and reſtored France to her former reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and crowned her with her priſtine beautie. It is He whoſe acts may ſtand to inſtruct Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12264:45"/>their duties in ſucceeding ages. It is Hee that was like <hi>Dauid</hi> in his reigne, full of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and bleſſings, that reſembled Him in his zeale of pietie and iuſtice (the prime and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall pillers of a Royaltie) who ruled his people happily, to the glorie of God, the good of his Subiects, and the conſolation of his owne Soule. Indeed, infinite were the vertues of this royall Prince, who ſucceeded his famons Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, who were ſo worthie, as they may adde glorie to his immortall fame and memorie: For He was lineally deſcended, in direct maſculine and lawfull line of <hi>Lewis,</hi> for his ſingular pietie, ſirnamed Saint, the 44<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. French King, whoſe quiuer was full of ſuch arrowes, as <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth bleſſings, to wit children, as <hi>Philip</hi> the Hardie, his Succeſſour in the Crowne, <hi>Peter</hi> Earle of Alancon, <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of Alancon, through <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> vntimely deceaſe, and alſo <hi>Robert</hi> the eldeſt and the youngeſt, were fortunate in leauing Iſſue, in whom they might liue after their deaths; the other died without heires ſprung from their owne loynes. The Iſſue of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Philip</hi> the Hardie ſucceeded lineally, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, King of France &amp; Poland, in whom the name and family of the Valor
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12264:45"/>being extinct, the Crowne fell to the Race of <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of Cleremont, who by <hi>Beautrix,</hi> ſole heire and daughter of <hi>Archibald</hi> Earle of Burbon, had <hi>Lewis</hi> afterwards created Duke: The which <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of Burbon, had Iſſue by <hi>Marie,</hi> daughter to <hi>Iohn</hi> the eighteenth Earle of Hainhault, had <hi>Peter</hi> Duke of Burbon, and <hi>Iames</hi> Earle of Ponthieu, Conſtable of France: <hi>Peter</hi> had by <hi>Iſabel,</hi> daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of Valois, <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Iames; Lewis</hi> ſirnamed the Good Duke of Burbon, had by <hi>Anne,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Auergne, <hi>Lewis</hi> Earle of Cleremont (deceaſing without Issue) <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Iames; Iohn</hi> had by <hi>Bonne,</hi> Dutcheſſe of Auergne &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Montpenſiere, <hi>Charles,</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> of Montpenſiere, father of <hi>Gilbert,</hi> of whom iſſued <hi>Charles</hi> the laſt Duke of Burbon; the which <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of Burbon, had by <hi>Agnes</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of Burgoigne, <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Peter; Iohn</hi> the ſecond of that name was linked in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with <hi>Ioane</hi> of France, daughter to <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeuenth, who dying without lawfull Iſſue, the name and armes of Duke went to <hi>Peter</hi> his younger brother: <hi>Peter</hi> the ſecond of that name Duke of Burbon, maried <hi>Anne</hi> of France, daughter to <hi>Lewis</hi> the deuenth, and had Iſſue
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12264:46"/>by her, one onely daughter, <hi>Suſan</hi> the generall heire of Bourbon, who was wife to the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Charles</hi> the youngeſt ſonne of <hi>Lewis</hi> abouenamed, Earle of Montpenſiere, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of Burbon; but no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren iſſuing from this mariage, the branch of the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of Burbon was broken off, and ended in this <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of Bourbon and Conſtable of France, who died at the ſiege of Rome. Now the Dutchie of Bourbonois being incorporated into the Crowne of France, it fell to the line of <hi>Iames</hi> of Ponthieu Conſtable of France, they youngeſt ſon of <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of Bourbon, the which <hi>Iames</hi> had by <hi>Ioane</hi> daughter of the Earle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul, <hi>Iohn</hi> his Succeſſour Earle of La March; <hi>Iohn</hi> had of <hi>Catherine,</hi> the onely daughter and heire of <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of Vendoſme, <hi>Iames</hi> King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who leauing no Iſſue Male, the right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance was tranſported to <hi>Lewis</hi> the younger brother; <hi>Lewis</hi> had no Iſſue by <hi>Iane</hi> of Ruſſy his firſt wife, but by his ſecond mariage he had <hi>Iohn</hi> his Succeſſour and Earle of Vendoſme: <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſecond had by <hi>Iean</hi> of Beauire, <hi>Francis</hi> his Succeſſour and Earle of Vendoſme, and <hi>Lewis</hi> Prince of La Roch Syr-you, who of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12264:46"/>
               <hi>Louiſe</hi> of Bourbon, the daughter of <hi>Gilbert</hi> of Bourbon, left <hi>Lewis</hi> of Bourbon Earle of Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſiere, you was father to <hi>Francis</hi> Duke of Bourbon, and Earle of Montpenſiere, who was father to <hi>Henrie</hi> laſt Duke of Montpenſiere, Prince of Dombos, Daulphine of Auergne, Lieutenant Generall for the King in Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and husband to <hi>Catherine Henrette</hi> of Ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euze, a Prince ſo famous for all vertues, as hee was admired of all. To <hi>Francis</hi> were borne, by <hi>Marie</hi> of Luxenburg, Counteſſe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul, and daughter of <hi>Peter</hi> of Luxenburg, <hi>Charles,</hi> Earle; but created Duke of Vendoſme, by King <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> the firſt. <hi>Francis</hi> Earle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul, who by <hi>Adrian</hi> Dutcheſſe of Eſterhout ville, had <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> who died young, <hi>Lewis</hi> Cardinall of Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, <hi>Antoniette</hi> wife to <hi>Claude</hi> of Lorraine Duke of Guiſe, alſo <hi>Louis Abbas</hi> of Fonteuaraux. <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt Duke of Vendoſme, had by <hi>Louis</hi> the daughter of <hi>Rene</hi> Duke of Alancon, <hi>Lewis,</hi> who died at the age of ſeuen yeeres; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie,</hi> who ſucceeded in his right, and was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards King of Nauarre; <hi>Francis</hi> Earle of Anghien; <hi>Charles,</hi> Cardinall Arch-Biſhop of Rouan; <hi>Iohn,</hi> who loſt his life at the battell of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Quintin; and <hi>Lewis</hi> Prince of Conde. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:12264:47"/>the Succeſſour of <hi>Charles</hi> firſt Duke of Vendoſme, and King of Nauarre, had by <hi>Ioane</hi> of Albret Queen of Nauarre (daughter to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the ſecond of that name, King of Nauarre) <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth of that name French King, as his Fathers Succeſſour, and the third of that name King of Nauarre, by the right of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This is the Royall Root from whence this Princely Branch is ſprung, which ſhewes the nobleneſſe of her deſcent: ſo that as Shee graceth her parentage by her vertues, ſo They grace Her by her birth: For howſoeuer wine be good out of a woodden diſh, yet we eſteeme it better, if we drinke it out of a golden veſſell: So howſoeuer vertuous noble perſonages, though ignobly borne, ought to bee reſpected, yet thoſe which haue vertue ioyned with their nobilitie of birth, are worthie of double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: Then who more to bereuerenced in our hearts, extolled in our ſpeeches, than this noble, and neuer-enough to bee honoured Ladie? who is deſcended by the fathers ſide, from <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, French King, who no whit vnworthie of his famous renowned Anceſtors, added luſter to their former glorie, who reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Common-wealth more than Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12264:47"/>indeed onely louing Himſelfe, becauſe He loued the Common-wealth, was not onely the Father of his Countrey, but alſo of the peace and tranquillitie of his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>But perhaps ſome will ſay, the childe is not alwayes the inheritour of the fathers worth: For neither the ſoule nor the vertues of it come by propagation, and the onely iuyce wee draw from our parents loynes, is their infirmities. Moreouer, though the childe hath not often the fathers wiſdome, yet for the moſt part it hath the mothers wit, will, and affections. Doe but ſearch Chronicles and Hiſtories for her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vertues, and you ſhall finde Her afore her mariage, the moſt vertuous Virgin; after her mariage, ſo worthie a Matron, as Heauen could ioy in, or earth be proud of: To ſpeake her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in particular, were a burthen heauier than Aetna; to paſſe them ouer in generall, were a wrong to her perfections; to vndertake to write of them ſeuerally, were pride in my pen; and to ſpeake of them, but ioyntly and briefly, were an argument of pouertie of inuention. To auoyd therefore both theſe enormities, let it be my ambition, to vſe that commendations of Her, at her entertainment and arriuall in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12264:48"/>France, formerly vttered by <hi>Monſieur du Varais,</hi> who making an Oration to Her, in which hee ſeemed to build the whole felicitie of France, vpon her mariage with the King, hee praiſeth her perfections in theſe words.</p>
            <p>Seeing in you ſo many graces, wherewith Nature hath endowed you, admiring the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wherewith ſhee hath adorned you, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that naturall ſweetneſſe wherewith ſhee hath tempered your royall grauitie, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with our eares the voice renowned by fame, which proclaimes the quickneſſe of your ſpirit, the ſoundneſſe of your iudgement, the eloquence of your diſcourſe, and that which exceeds all, the incomparable commendation of your holy and religious diſpoſition; wee perſwade our ſelues that you are Shee, whom the Heauens had appointed by your pleaſing companie, to mollifie the life of the King, to prolong his dayes by his content, and to make his reigne perpetuall, by the continuance of a great and happie poſteritie. Wee beleeue that you are onely She vpon earth, worthie to make the life of the moſt triumphant King in the world, to reſt in your chaſte boſome; and that He, aboue all others, did merit to embrace the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12264:48"/>moſt vertuous and pleaſing Princeſſe in his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious armes. Whereby we preſage we ſhall ſoone ſee a number of goodly children carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their fore-heads their fathers valour, their mothers vertue, the greatneſſe and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the houſe of France, whereunto you are allied, the happineſſe and power of the houſe of Auſtria, from whence you are iſſued, and the wiſdom of Florence, in which you were borne. To the beleefe of this preſage all things ſeem to inuite vs, but cheefly the Heauen &amp; the Sea for we ſee at the arriuall of your Maieſtie, the Sea full of ſtormes is growne calme, &amp; the Heauen ouercaſt with clouds is cleere, as if they woud, with a pleaſing eye, celebrate with vs the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of your reception. For in good time then, oh great Queene, are you come into our coaſts, long may you liue happie in France, and to France, that the age in which wee liue, may terme you a happie wife to a King, and future ages, a happie mother of Kings.</p>
            <p>Here then you may diſcerne the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perfections of this moſt excellent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes mother, who caried herſelfe ſo ſubmiſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her Lord the King, that nothing was more deere or neere vnto Him, than Herſelfe, ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12264:49"/>and royally to her Subiects, that Shee won the hearts of all thoſe, whoſe ſoules and affections were ſealed and deliuered to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; ſo worthily to her children, that not onely by her inſtructions, but her example (which children are moſt apt and readie to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) She incited them to goodneſſe, hauing a diligent care, that good education might water thoſe good ſeeds of vertue and bleſt endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which Nature had planted in them: For howſoeuer the Root, from whence this royall Stem ſprang, and the Father of this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, had verie ſhort continuance in the weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome pilgrimage of this world (as who ſhould ſay, the Heauens ſaw it not conuenient, that he ſhould any longer liue, when another came to be an Inheritrix of his vertues, and Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of his perfections) whereby Shoe might ſeeme to haue ſome want of her Progenitours care, to ſee Her brought vp in all vertuous lore, neceſſarie or requiſite for the accompliſhment of ſo great a Princeſſe, yet her mother, and not onely her mother, but her mothers care, ſtill ſuruiuing and outliuing her father, hath ſo edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and nouriſhed vp this Princely Sprig (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indeed of Herſelfe, Shee was declining
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12264:49"/>from all euill, and enclining to all goodneſſe) that She wanted nothing to make Her moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in all rare vertues and qualities; for her religion hauing a principall care (as She ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that Shee ſhould bee inſtructed in the truth and Chriſtian faith, the which this mightie Queene profeſſed, as Catholique and vniuerſall) in the which howſoeuer there bee ſome poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, like the Coloquintida in the Iewes pot, which ſpoileth all the pottage, as Iuſtification by merits; Adoration of Images, which cannot heare vs; Prayer to Saints, which cannot helpe vs; for the dead, which cannot be helped; Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, Maſſe, Abſolution of ſinnes to any, though impenitent; yet notwithſtanding there be many practiſes allowable, as holy pious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in which She was taught to be abounding, as ſatisfaction, if it may, be for offences commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt our brethren, as frequent and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent prayer to God, to beautifie our ſoules reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious faſting, to mortifie our bodies; as conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie (which many of the Romiſh Religion profeſſe, but few of their Friers, Monks, Nuns, or Ieſuites practiſe) And truely She hath beene wiſe hearted, and choſen the better part; for although by her mothers, ſuppoſed good,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12264:50"/>though truely miſconceiued opinion, She hath beene brought vp in the Romiſh Religion, yet like the induſtrious Bee. And howſoeuer Shee might erre in ſome things, for want of true iudgement, which cannot be expected in ſuch tender yeeres, eſpecially the ſemall ſex, who are moſt readie to be ſeduced, and to walke as their, leaders guide them, being moſt credulous, and the weaker veſſells, yet reaſon and charitie may depoſe, that a Princeſſe of ſuch ripeneſſe of wit, and incomparable vnderſtanding, may eaſily be brought from giuing any internall worſhip with her heart, though She may externall with her bodie to anie Image. Oh no; Shee ſcornes to worſhip a thing more baſe than any of her baſeſt ſeruants; nay, of a lower condition than any of the meaneſt liuing creatures; for the trees grow, and are clad in varietie of garments, hauing their ſummer and their winter ſuit, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on in the Spring a veſture of greene, and in Autumne their gray cloathing. Morcouer, the flowers of the field are the work manſhip of God; and therefore certes, more excellent than the childe of mans induſtrie and inuention: but an Image hath not power to cloath in ſelfe, as the plants and, flowers, but is the effect of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12264:50"/>mans labour, and is onely clad in that array, the which the Painter hath giuen it; the trees en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and bring forth fruit for our ſuſtenance, but an Image hath onely the figure according to which the Caruer cut it, neither yeeldeth it any profit, but diſhonour to God, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to them that honour it.</p>
            <p>And if it bee thus, much leſſe then a vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, by how much leſſe to bee eſteemed than a ſenſitiue creature; for they moue, ſee, heare, taſte, ſmell, and feele; but an Image is voyd of motion, and without the helpe of others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to the ſame manſion-place, blinde and like <hi>Iacob,</hi> cannot ſee when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> doth him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, deafe cannot heare what thou ſpeakeſt, and in euerie reſpect ſenſleſſe: But how much inferiour is it to man, yea euen to the pooreſt miſerable mortall; for looke vpon his ſoule, it the Image of God his Maker; looke vpon his bodie, and euerie organ performes its office, the eye ſees, the eare heares, the palat tafteth, the palme toucheth, the noſe ſenteth, the foot walketh, the hand worketh, and that which is more, the heart vnderſtandeth.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, if any thing but God were to be worſhipped, it were this little world, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12264:51"/>yet great world of wonders, this maſter-peece of Gods workmanſhip, called Man. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I deeme it a leſſe errour with the ignorant Indians, to worſhip the Sun and the Moone, for they are heauenly creatures; a ſmaller fault in the Aegyptians, to adore an onion, for that was their chiefeſt ſuſtenance; in the people of Iſrael, for he was a King, nay a God on earth, for ſo God ſtiles Princes, than to proſtrate and caſt downe ones ſelfe to an Image: Farre bee it therefore to commit ſuch ſacriledge to her ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie, or that our imaginations ſhould rob Her of ſo much ſenſe and ſauing knowledge, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that Shee will not bee brought from the adoration of Images, if now Shee doth, or euer will adore a ſenſleſſe blocke, a ſtocke, or it may be indeed, She may doe it ſome outward reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as one may doe to a picture, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his friend, or in the reſpect they beare to him whom it repreſents. Neither is it poſſible, but She will be inſtructed, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer doth truſt to his owne merits, doth relye vpon a broken reed, and buildeth the houle of his ſaluation, vpon the ſands of his own works, which is readie each moment to bee ruined with euerie ſtormie tempeſt of the Deuils
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12264:51"/>temptations; but hee that doth build vpon the Corner-ſtone and Rocke <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> his foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation being faſt and firme, his building is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall and euerlaſting: Shee, without doubt, will conſider, that the beſt of our deeds is ſin, and the beſt of our deſerts damnation, that all our works are but as a menſtruous cloth, ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with impuritie; that when wee haue done all wee can, wee are but vnprofitable ſeruants; and that although good works iuſtifie the faith, yet faith iuſtifies the man, that though works proue faith to bee liuing in the man, yet faith proueth the man to be liuing in Chriſt; that as faith without works is like the barren fig tree, or like the wombes oi <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> fruitleſſe; ſo works without faith are of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, it is not to bee beleeued, but that She will be brought to beleeue, that prayers to Saints cannot ought auaile Her, that whe She prayes vnto them, they haue no eares to heare Her, or if they haue eares to heare Her, yet it may be they want hearts to pitie Her; or if they haue hearts to pitie Her, yet they want hands to helpe Her: Shee will eaſily therefore vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. that her prayers ought to bee directed to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12264:52"/>the Fountaine of all goodneſſe, the Giuer of all good gifts, that as He is her Lord for power, ſo Hee is her God for pitie, whoſe will is not fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate for want of power, nor his abilitie vnexer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed for want of will, but being omnipotent, He is omniuolent to helpe Her in all her neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities: It is He which hath commanded Her to call vpon Him, which hath promiſed to heare and to helpe Her: and ſurely, She will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the fountaine of liuing water, to ſeeke the puddles which were digged by humane inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are as drie as the barren Arabian Deſert, in which is no comfort.</p>
            <p>Neither is it to be deſpaired of, that She will vnderſtand, that each Chriſtian ſoule hath its purgatorie in this life; for he runneth thorow a world of miſeries and afflictions, that his ſoule is purged and cleanſed by the bloud of Chriſt, from all our ſinnes; that our Sauiour Chriſt maketh mention but of two waves, the ſtraight and narrow, leading to euerlaſting bliſſe; the other broad, bringing vs to the pit of deſtruction: and if there bee but two wayes, there be but two homes, to wit, <hi>Diues</hi> his infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> his reſting place, <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome. It may be indeed ſome Deuill, in the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12264:52"/>ſhape of an Angell of light, may perſwade Her of a third place, alledging Scripture, wreſted from the proper ſenſe, for their poſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter, Chriſt hath once ſuffered for our ſinnes, the Iuſt for the vniuſt, that He might bring vs to God, and was put to death concerning the fleſh, but quickned in the Spirit, by the which Spirit He went and preached vnto the ſpirits which are in priſon, which were ſometimes diſobedient in the dayes of Noah, while the Arke was preparing; wherein few, that is eight ſoules, were ſaued in the water.</hi> But how can they from hence proue Purgatorie; for was not Chriſts Spirit from the beginning? Hath not his Spirit from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning beene in the mouths of his Miniſters, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Preachers? And is not <hi>Noah,</hi> in the ſecond Chapter of the next Epiſtle, termed a Pracher of righteouſneſſe? Did not alſo <hi>Noah</hi> preach faithfully to that incredulous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious people, which ſtopt their eares &amp; would not bee reformed? Therefore the Text ſaith, were then drowned, and are now in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and without Gods Spirit did preach vnto them, as it doth now by his Miniſters. There is alſo great hope, that She will be won neither to feare the Popes Bull, or eſteeme his pardons;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12264:53"/>for who can forgiue the offence, but he which is offended? Can the Subiect remit any fault committed againſt the Soueraigne? We know Gods Miniſters haue a great prerogatiue, and that whatſoeuer they binde or looſe on earth, ſhall be bound or looſed in Heauen: and wee reade that <hi>Balaams</hi> bleſſing was of great eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet <hi>Balaam</hi> muſt haue a care, not to bleſſe thoſe whom God curſeth, nor to curſe thoſe whom God bleſſeth; for then it is in vaine, and ſhall light vpon his owne head. Neither hath the Pope, or any Prieſt, power to abſolue any abſolutely, but only ſuch as God doth pardon, and conditionally vpon faith and repentance: I doe confeſſe, that ſinnes vnconfeſſed, are as winde in the earth, the which if not vented, will cauſe an earthquake in the conſcience; and it is a great eaſe to acknowledge our ſinnes to Gods Miniſter, and abſolution from his lips, is as a kinde of confirmation and ſeale of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of them, in regard he is Gods Angell; for ſo God termes the Miniſters of the ſeuen Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the Reuelation, they are his Meſſengers and Embaſſadours ſent vnto mortalls, to bring vnto them glad tydings of peace, and to preach unto them remiſſion of ſinnes: but when his
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12264:53"/>pardon fals where there is no penetecie,&amp; his abſolution on a ſoule which is not broken, and on an vncontrite heart, it is like drops of raine and timely ſhowers diſtilled vpon a ſlintie rocke, the which in regard it is denied entrance, it makes no abode vpon it; for is any man ſo mad, to thinke his ſinnes to be forgiuen, which is giuen ouer to worke vncleanneſſe? Or any man to beleeue, that he is a holy veſſell, when hee is filled with the dregs of Satan, and his owne corruptions? Is any man ſo mad, to thinke his ſinnes are pardoned, when hee hath not wept for thoſe ſinnes which hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and doth ſtill commit ſinnes, and that willingly, which he ought to weepe for? And therefore She will be, and is truely penitent, that She may be truely abſolued; She is abſtinent, that She might be continent; and temperate, that She might not be brought or wrought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vnchaſtitie. And me thinkes She ſpeakes to our Prince, as the Church to Chriſt in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, <hi>Draw me, and I will follow after thee:</hi> ſuch is her conſcience.</p>
            <p>For looke into her education for her cariage, and you ſhall ſee that Shee is enſtructed in all manner of courtly and courteous behauiour,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12264:54"/>carying Herſelfe humbly to her inferiors, yet honourably amongſt her equals; that her ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtately cariage to the one might not make them deiected, nor her too much ſubmiſſiue behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the other, make them too high concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for as her excellencies put all pride out of her countenance, ſo She is not voyd of pride, by being ignorant of her excellencies, but by making all her excellencies voyd of pride; and howſoeuer Nature hath ſo framed her heauenly lights, that there appeares a Pariſetene when her eyes be open, yet the two more ſhining gueſts of meekneſſe and Maieſtie, like two good Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, beautifie and adorne that lodging. And howſoeuer her breath is more ſweet, than gentle <hi>Zephyrus</hi> creeping vpon the boſome of <hi>Flora,</hi> yet the ſweet delightfull <hi>Philomels</hi> ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tunes, caried in that breath, are more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: And as Grace hath taught Her to rule the paſſions of her minde, ſo Art hath enſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed Her to rule the parts of her bodie, and like a well-framed Engine, each part obſerues the due and true motion. Indeed, what can be that is worthie in a Princeſſe, which is not in Her? What rareneſſe of education and behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, either for the captiuating, or the keeping a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12264:54"/>Princes affections; for though indeed vertue is the greateſt beautie, yet had She nothing but her beautie, yet no mortall (whoſe ambitious eye durſt ſoare at ſo high an obiect) could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, but hee muſt confeſſe, nor confeſſe, but admire, nor admire, but loue ſo rare perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as are pourtrayed in her beautifull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and amiable proportion. A creature ſo faire, as except Fame it ſelfe will be infamous, it dares not ſtile any fairer; and that which makes an addition to her faireneſſe, is that her beautifull bodie is but the cloathing of a more beautifull minde, a minde fraught and full of wit, more readie to cenſure, than to ſhew it ſelfe; her words being as rare as precious: who is ſilent, but not ſullen; modeſt, without affectation; ſhamefaſte, without ignorance: whoſe eyes are like the palaces of <hi>Cupid,</hi> and yet ſets reaſon vpon the deſires of all the beholders, and teacheth the ſpectatours chaſtitie; whoſe face being the true frontiſpice of her minde, is the ſeat of ſweetneſſe and ſoueraigntie; whoſe cheekes are like gardens of Roſes and Lillies, and Alablaſter beſprinckled with Vermilion: both of which are the ineffable ornaments of Nature.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:12264:55"/>
            <p>Alas, what ſhould I ſay more of the rare compoſure of her Angell-like celeſtiall counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, in the framing of which, Nature hath ſhewed herſelfe no ſtep-mother, but hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted the perfection of her affection vnto that ſex in Her, whoſe praiſes ſince I cannot vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in ſpeeches, let it be ſufficient to admire in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Not to omit the proportion of her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, in the diſcourſe of which the moſt eloquent Oratour might finde a moſt ſpacious field to walke in; the which is like her minde, neither too loftie, nor too exceſſiue low; but her ſtature is indifferent, and in the meane, as if Nature in framing of Her, had beene the Ape of Vertue, and intended to dwell in the meane, and ſhame both extremes; each ligament and lineament of her bodie is ſo ſtrongly, and yet ſo ſweetly framed, as indeed they claime the admiration of all, and the affections of the moſt Peereleſſe Prince in the world.</p>
            <p>As for the portion, which indeed is in the laſt and leaſt place to be reſpected; what Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe can equall Her? For what greater portion than happineſſe? and what greater happineſſe, than that which Shee will bring tome King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, into which She ſhall match, and in the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12264:55"/>which She ſhall be reſident? whoſe Allies ſhall bee as ſtrong Bulwarks to the place, to whoſe Prince She ſhall be conioyned in wedlocke, in the time of warre; and in the time of peace, the meanes of the tranſporting of all neceſſarie and requiſite benefits to that Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thus her vertue, her parentage, her educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, proportion, and portion, proue Her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be linked with the Worthieſt in mariage, theſe make Her fit to bee a Wife; but the intire affection which Shee beareth to our Prince, proue Her worthie to bee his Wife; and no doubt, but as there is the higheſt degree of loue betwixt Them, ſo no doubt they ſhall haue the pledges of true loue, and ſhall liue and giue life to this Kingdome hereafter by their poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Thus it appeareth, that as now She is euerie wayes a moſt excellent Virgin; ſo if vertue, edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, parentage, portion, proportion, loue, all theſe, or any of theſe, may make a happie Spouſe, She is likely to make a moſt bleſſed Yoake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow; theſe make Her fit to be a Wiſe, but her loue to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> his Wife; her vertues ioy the world in generall, but her loue to Him, doth ſolace Him in particular; and who is able to deſcribe her loue? not man, for they are not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12264:56"/>ſo violent in their paſſions; not women, for few or none of them are ſo vertuous, to loue ſo chaſtely affectionate: no ſurely, neither man nor woman can relate it to the meaſure, althogh they may vtter ſome part of the manner of it; for her loue is euen like her vertues, infinite, Oh the incomprehenſible wiſdome of the Deitie! which euen afore our birth, doth not onely foreknow, but doth alſo predetermine all the actions and affections or vs mortals, effecting things, and that for our welfare, euen by almoſt ſeeming impoſſible meanes, beyond our hope or imagination: Who would haue thought that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould haue found a Kingdome, when he went to looke his fathers Aſſes? Or <hi>Dauid</hi> a Crowne, when hee went to carie releefe to his brethren? God oftentimes ſhewes vs our home in the midſt of our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; for ſo did Hee deale with our mightie Prince, who manifeſting a high degree of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in looking afore He leapt; and ſhewed no leſſe religion than diſcretion, in vndertaking though a tedious iourney, to view the Cabinet into which Hee was to put his Soule, and to place his perpetuall welfare, before He truſted it with the cuſtodie of it, moſt fortunately met
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12264:56"/>with the Center of his affections, euen in the mid way; Hee aimed, but God directed the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of his loue at a more happie marke, more happie and leſſe dangerous for Himſelfe, more happie &amp; more proſperous for his Countries; In ſo much, me thinkes, that ſo ſoone as the louely pourtraicture of this Peereleſſe Prince (though by his picture) ſhould bee conucyed thorow thoſe Cryſtall Caſements of her affections, into the cloſet of her ſecrecies, it ſhould cauſe her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall facultie thus to rationate with it ſelfe in ſilence: Whither wandereſt thou, ſweet Prince, ſo far from thy home? Thou art lodged in my heart: Oh let it be thy perpetuall habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: Why doeſt thou carrie my heart ſo far from my bodie? It is thou which doeſt now poſſeſſe it; for I am no more Miſtreſſe of that which was mine owne: Why ſhouldeſt thou ſeeke far for that which isneerer home? Expoſe not thy ſelfe to the dangers &amp; troubles of trauel: ſaile not into an Ocean of ſorrowes, when thou mayſt lie at roade in a more quiet Harbour. Oh let my loue be the load-ſtone of thy perſon, &amp; the Remora of thy affections: But if thou wilt needs trauell into the Weſterne parts, and make a night of ſorrow in our Hemiſphere; yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12264:57"/>turne to vs againe, and let the brightneſſe of thy beames expell the darkneſſe of our dolour. No doubt but our Prince was inflamed, before He ſaw the ſmoake of her deſire: her lookes were the meſſengers of loue, and his heart was open to entertaine the embaſſage: They were the darts of <hi>Cupid,</hi> and his heart was ioyous in being wounded with ſuch weapons: Thus did they meet in their affections, and the Almightie ſeeing (if mortals can merit any thing) that The deſerued what They deſired, will ioyne their hands as well as their harts, &amp; make Them one really, as they are mentally. Happie there. fore (oh royall King) which ſhall liue to ſee your childrens children flouriſhing in your Palaces, &amp; theſe Kingdoms eternally conferred &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed vpon your poſteritie. Happie, ô Prince, who ſhall be linked to one which is the Golden Chaine of Vertue, this Diamond of the world, whom Nature hath ſo preciouſly ſet in the eyes of men, to bee the chiefe worke of her work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, and the Ornament of the world. Oh happie Princeſſe, ſo happie in finding ſuch a Head, whoſe welfare ſhall be guarded by ſuch a Prince, that you ſhall ſeeme like ſweet Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water kept in a cryſtall glaſſe: Who when you
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12264:57"/>reioyce, ſhall ſee your ioy ſhine in an other; and when you grieue, ſhall ſee the face of your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in anothers melting liquid heart. Oh hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie both of you, when like two heauenly Strings conioyned together, you ſhall make a ſweeter harmonie: Oh how delightfull will the name of Parents bee vnto you, when they ſhall ſee your Children flouriſh, in whom they are. Oh what an ineffable bliſſe it will bee, when they ſhall ſee their children with awfull loue runne about them, and like little modells of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, carrie themſelues about them. Oh hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie pie England! which art like neuer to bee like a flocke of ſheepe without a Shepherd, or an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie diſcomfited without a Leader; but haſt more than hopes, neuer to want one of thy bleſſed Kings Race to ſit vpon thy Throne, ſo long as the Sunne and Moone endureth which haſt likewiſe the number of thy friends increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, more than the multitudes of thine enemies is augmented. Oh happie France! who gaueſt birth to a Princeſſe, which giueth life to thee, &amp; promiſeth ſafetie to thy Confines, which is the Ornament of thee, as thou art the Ornament of the world, which mayſt ioy in each benefit thou affoordeſt, yet in nothing more than Her.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:12264:58"/>
            <p>Happie in this Contract is Chriſtendome; for although now it may for a time endure the corroſiue of war, yet it ſhall be healed with the plaſter of peace; and a wrangling mother ſhall beget a quiet daughter; and the purifying of the aire ſhall bee the iſſue of ſtorme and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Happie in this Contract are Chriſtians; for they ſee the bow of the wicked broken, and the horne of the righteous exalted; the woman in trauaile ſhall forſake the deſert; the Church ſhall put off her mourning weeds, and put on the robes of comfort; the name of Chriſt and the Goſpell ſhall bee exalted, and the man of ſinne and perdition caſt into euerlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>But ſtill me thinks there be ſome ſicke quea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſtomackt people, who diſtaſte all ſweet deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, and onely delight in ſowre and vnſauory ſallets, who haue ſuch timorous tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as they feare where there is no danger, making that, which otherwayes (well applied) ſhould be the cauſe of their reſt, the mother of diſquiet, fearing leſt this Contract ſhould bring an innouation of religion. For (ſay they) was not, I pray you, <hi>Salomon</hi> ſeduced and brought to idolatrie, by marying? Did not <hi>Abraham</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12264:58"/>
               <hi>Eleazar</hi> his ſeruant, nay bound him by an oath, not to take his ſonne a wiſe amongſt the Canaanites, but his owne kinred? and were not the Iewes forbidden to match with the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then? Tis true; but it is a queſtion, whether this was any otherwayes ceremonially enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Iewes, and not neceſſarily impoſed vpon the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, if the ſeruant of <hi>Abraham</hi> could not haue found a woman for <hi>Iſaak,</hi> that would haue come with him, hee had beene diſcharged of his oath: Likewiſe Prince alſo are publique perſons, and ought to be Supporters of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique welfare; and therefore that mariage may be lawfull for Him, which ſeemeth inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a priuate man, in regard that Hee is not ſo much to reſpect that which may bee for his owne, but his peoples welfare; No doubt, could <hi>Ioſeph</hi> haue well forſake Aegypt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the preiudice of the Country, &amp; inferring a generall diſcommoditie, he would haue diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe, it may be, with more ioy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment; but God had allotted, that by his meanes Aegypt ſhould be preſerued; nay, and I may well ſay, not ſo much Aegypt as Iſrael might haue ſafetie, therefore <hi>Ioſeph</hi> muſt bee
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12264:59"/>brought into Aegypt by a ſtrange meanes mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with a ſtrange women: and what was all this to intimate, but that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was ſold to Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, that Iſrael might be preſerued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> famine: and no doubt Gods wiſedome doth oftentimes ſee beyond the reach of mans apprehenſion, and may match a diuerſity of Religion to make an vniformity of faith, to the end that there may bee one Shepherd, one ſheepefold, one Chriſt, one Chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>For is not in her breſt the whole globe of this worlds worth contained? is not her boſome a ſtately Theater in which each ſeuerall vertue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth a liuely part? is not the Iuory compared to her whitenes, and Aurora pale being ioyned to her bluſhes; her bluſhes, the which modeſty doth alwayes dye, which notwithſtanding doth alwayes liue in her countenance, whoſe matchleſſe vertue is not like a Pearle found in a dunghill, but dwelling in ſo faire a lodging: It is ſhe only whoſe beautiful form is ſuch rare phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, as it is able to make an old Prince young, and to make a young Prince liue till he be aged. True, but it is an ancient poſition, that ſtately buildings muſt haue great meanes to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them, and ſuch rare beauties, rich reuenues
<pb facs="tcp:12264:59"/>to vphold their luſter, for the whiteſt cloth doth ſooneſt take ſoyle, the richeſt veſture ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſpoyled, if not well looked to, and the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt creature moſt ſubiect to be deformed, and wrinckled with want, pouerty, and afflictions. It is requiſite therefore that your moſt curious workemanſhips ſhould be moſt curiouſly kept, that pictures excellently drawne, ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently preſerued. God therefore, with whom all things paſt, and to come, are preſent, foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the excellency of this modell of true per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, gaue her beautie to her vertues, and meanes to her beauty; for what Princeſſe in <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall haue a richer dowry? The treaſure which followes her as a ſeruant whitherſoeuer ſhee goeth is in finite; and as ſhee wanteth no wealth her ſelfe, ſo that Kingdome ſhall want no riches which doth enioy her; for what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter riches than happineſſe, and what greater happineſſe than that which ſhe bringeth to the place ſhee ſhall inhabit? Is it worth or ſame which they thirſt after? what greater fame than her beauty? and yet her beauty leſſe than her leaſt vertue: Surely, that Kingdome ſhall need no ſunne, in which her vertue ſhineth; that Hemiſphere no light, in which ſuch a light is
<pb facs="tcp:12264:60"/>reſplendent; no riches in which is ſuch a Iewel Neither is ſhe meanely powerfull in her migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Allies, for as ſhe is neere to all men in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (for what heart can hate ſo harmleſſe a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) ſo ſhe is deare to many Princes by affinity, as to her brother in vertues, as well as by birth, <hi>Lewis</hi> the 13, King of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> a Prince ſo vertuous, ſo valiant, that the one might make him proſperous in peace, the other trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant in victories, for hee is not onely his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heire in his Kingdome, but is like to be his ſucceſſour in his conqueſts; for though his face as yet doth ſcarce ſhew his ſex, yet his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude prooues him a man, a man of ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uict courage, and incredible force, that few can equall, none exceed him; for though time as yet hath not much outſtript him, in regard of his tender yeares, yet hee hath outſtript time, who indeed ſo farre goes beyond all his time and yeares, that whereas others ſeeme to watch and catch time, which alwaies ſtealeth away with a gliding ſlie pace, yet hee ſeemeth to flie from time, &amp; time to run after to catch him; in ſo much, as when following times ſhall reade the ſtorie (or rather the beginning) of his life, they ſhall admire to ſee one ſo young in yeares
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:12264:60"/>and courage, ſo old in wiſdome and experience, and ſhall thinke by his preſident, that diſcretion hath ſhaked hands with the gray head, &amp; hoarie haires, as an houſe ouerweake and vnworthy of ſuch an inhabitant, and taken the Caſtle to defend her ſelfe againſt her enemies, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and vnchaſtitie, rage, fury, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like troopes of aduerſe enemies, and enuious aduerſaries, for though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance and vnchaſtitie are vſuall (I had almoſt ſaid, for ſo they are accounted, veniall) ſinnes; yet He is a rider and ruler of his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, reyneth in his luſts with the bridle of wiſedome: others, if they be diſtaſted in the ſtrength of their youth, haue ſuch heat of bloud, and doe boyle in anger, that they ſeeme to haue enough fury to furniſh all the furies in hell, and yet notwithſtanding themſelues ſtill haue heaped meaſure, throwing themſelues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on each apparent danger, without conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or feare, doing any iniury without conſcience and religion, but wiſely foreſees a danger, and ſeekes to preuent it, and is ſo valiant, that Hee dares not fight but vpon iuſt occaſion. This is the royall Brother of ſo vertuous a Siſter; this is that mighty Monarch, with whom England
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12264:61"/>ſhakes not only the hands of friendſhip, but fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. And who is it but the moſt Illuſtrious Princeſſe the Lady <hi>Henrette Maria</hi> which puts the hands together? It is She whoſe twinne was happineſſe, and whoſe birth brought in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity to all this part; nay, to all the world, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to France and England; to France, for God (no doubt) foreſaw that he had ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtored it with Sonnes iſſued from that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of goodneſſe <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, whereby that bleſſed Countrey might ſeeme ſufficiently ſtrengthned and fortified in it ſelfe. God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in due time ſent it a daughter, ſo excelling and tranſcending in vertue &amp; beauty, to make it ſtrong without it ſelfe, and to make walls of friendſhip about it to England, for it was not obſcured from the All, and al wayes All-ſeeing eye of God, before the beginning of the world, much more Her being, what need England ſhould haue to helpe her Allies and Neighbours, though not her ſelfe; and therefore ordained two ſuch Potentates as K. <hi>Lewis</hi> of France, &amp; Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of England; and likewiſe ſent this worthy Princeſſe to ioyne theſe two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to make them Brothers who are ſo like one another in vertuous conditions, who
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:12264:61"/>are both magnanimous, both wife, both vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, and no doubt both of them ſhall be fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; they will draw their ſwords in Iuſtice, handle them with ſuch courage, as each blow ſhall ſeeme to be the poſtilion of death vnto their enemie; ſo that they ſhall ſatisfie their thirſtie blades with the bloud of Tyrants, and die their ſwords with the death of the enemies to truth and equitie.</p>
            <p>And who is the foundation vpon whom theſe hopes are erected, but vpon this gracious Princeſſe, who hath not onely vertue in Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, highneſſe of birth and good education in and from her Anceſtours greatneſſe of eſtate; but alſo hath beautie to moue loue, wit to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend to loue, and excellent bodie to content it, and a gratefull minde to reward it: For had She all theſe rare endowments and aptitudes of mariage, and yet had no inclination to wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, her rare gifts would be like precious iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, which loſe their luſter for want of wearing, like fragrant flowers in a moſt delightfull gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which are neuer gathered, but ſinde their tombe where they had their birth, like a root buried vp in the ground, which neuer bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: if She were reſolued not to make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12264:62"/>change of virginall for coniugall chaſtitie, She ſhould doe the world too much iniurie, in cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering vp Chriſtendomes ioyes, whoſe hopes are chiefly in Her, with Herſelfe.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, her vertues would returne to the King of Heauen, of whom they all hold <hi>in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite,</hi> for want of heires, and could onely finde life after her death in the mouth of Fame; her nobilitie of bloud would die in Herſelfe, for want of poſteritie to whom it might ſtill be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued; Shee would loſe the worth of her educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in not teaching that to others, which She hath beene taught Herſelfe, all that Shee could well diſpoſe of would be her Dowrie, to the w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the poore would be rightfull heires, and as for her beautie, it would periſh without bleſſing any but a multitude of wounded admiring ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators: And howſoeuer indeed it may bee Death could not take it away with her ſoule, yet the graue would conſume it with her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: She therefore, as Shee was the childe of a mother, ſo deſireth to be the mother of a childe.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, let no man bee guiltie of ſuch a fooliſh ſuſpition, once to doubt or imagine, that our Princes wiſdome ſhould be ouercome by a womans weakneſſe; that the eye of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12264:62"/>and religion ſhould bee put out with the eye of affection; Or farre be it to commit ſuch blaſphemie againſt his Highneſſe, either ſo much to diminiſh his conſtancie in the truth, or derogate from the ſoundnesse of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and iudgement, that euer Hee ſhould bee brought to forſake that, in the defenſe of which He would deeme the loſſe of his life and bloud precious: Will Hee relinquiſh that which is built vpon the ground of Gods word, which is diſagreeing in nothing, agreeing in euerie thing with the holy Scriptures, to be the Follower of mens traditions, and an Obſeruer and Seruer of the fooliſh inuentions of humane fancie, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence that termed Holines, which is but true Inſanctitie; to relye vpon any thing but the merits of Chriſt; to truſt to his owne workes, or deeme them meritorious, and ſo to make Himſelfe his owne Sauiour, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, the comming of Chriſt of no neceſſitie; to forſake that faith which was founded by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, vpheld and followed by the Fathers, whoſe antiquitie is ſuch, that it was preached by our Heuenly Father to our earthly parent in Paradiſe, by the which all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and future ages muſt bee ſaued, to follow
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12264:63"/>that which is but an vpſtart Irreligion; which was ſet vp by Couetouſneſſe and Ambition, which is to bring gold to the Popes coffers, not God to the peoples conſciences, which is only to hide the light of the Goſpell vnder the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell of an vnknowne tongue, to ſtarue the ſoules of poore people, which makes Ignorance the mother of Deuotion, which is Author of deſtruction; which maketh people thinke it nothing to ſinne, becauſe they thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſure of a pardon; which maketh adultery, Sodomie, fornication more honourable, than marriage allowable; which maketh <hi>Moſes</hi> infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to <hi>Aaron,</hi> which bringeth the neckes of Princes and Kings vnder the foot and follies of Antichriſt, which is the Nurſe of rebellion in Subiects againſt their Soueraigne, and maketh him a God which is but a deuill incarnate, who Lucifer-like prefumeth to ſit in the ſeat of God.</p>
            <p>Or what heart can be ſuch a detractor from Her vertue, to thinke that this Phoenix of her age, this noble Princeſſe, whoſe breſt is the Cottage of humility, and the quiet harbour of lowly thoughts, will offer to ſeeke to guide Him by whom She is to be directed, to be the ſterne
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12264:63"/>when She is but the veſſell of which Hee is the Pilot; to be the Sun, when ſhe is but the Moone, which muſt borrow light fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his knowledge? can She which eſteemes him to be all worth, thinke that the greateſt ornament in him is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy? No ſurely, She knowes that She may be the crowne of the head, but She will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to be the head of the body; She deſires not to metamorphiſe water into oyle. It is not hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from Her, that Nature and Grace hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen man the ſuperiority, that the ſtrength of his body, the ſtoutneſſe and courage of his minde, the ſtayedneſſe of his affections, the wiſedome of his ſoule, the pregnancy of his wit, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of his will, the ſoundneſſe of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ripeneſſe of his vnderſtanding, in a word, all the powers of his ſoule, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his body, doe pleade for and claime a Diadem of dominion and gouernment ouer women, which are the weaker ſex; She deſires but to reſt in his boſome, to be his heart, and not his head; She knowes that is his peculiar, and therefore She will not challenge it; She is the heart, and He is the head, the head in which is the eye of knowledge, the eare of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the gift of diſcretion; and will not the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12264:64"/>heart thinke as the eye informes it, as the eare certifies it, as diſcretion tels it? Yes ſurely, and She will do as her Prince inſtructs her; for will not She which loued himſelfe for himſelfe, loue God for him, and for herſelfe alſo? may not He which hath drawne her heart to loue him, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her ſoule to embrace God? Yes ſurely, there is ſmall doubt, great hope, nay almoſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that not onely She, but many millions will be brought and wrought to embrace the Chriſtian faith, to fauour and follow the true Religion, by the meanes of this happy vnion and bleſſed contract.</p>
            <p>Neither are theſe all the euidences for this ground of our happineſſe, but wee haue more mighty motiues to induce and perſwade vs that She will open her breſt to entertaine the truth, and vnfold Her armes to embrace affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately this our ancient Catholicke, Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, and reformed Religion. For can She call to remembrance her Grandmother <hi>Ioanna Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brettana</hi> Q. of Nauarre, the louing, chaſte, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, ſober, diſcreet wife of <hi>Anthony</hi> Duke of Burbon her Grandfather; can She (I ſay) retaine in her mind that delight of Heauen, and light of earth her Grandmother, and yet forget her
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12264:64"/>Religion, in the profeſſion of which She was conſtant and vnmoueable? And what was it, but that which wee now profeſſe, to wit, the faith which is according to knowledge, and not ignorance; for, how can they be good which know not what goodneſſe is? as the Layty of the Romiſh Church which is nurſt and nuſled vp in blindneſſe, the faith which teacheth vs to put on the roabe of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, to relye wholly and ſolely vpon his merits, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon our ſelues, and our owne actions, as death and darkneſſe, vnleſſe Chriſt giue life and light to vs and them. Thus was ſhe in practiſe pious, in profeſſion a Proteſtant, in which ſhee liued, in which ſhe dyed, by which now ſhe reſteth in peace, ſhall riſe in power, and reape a crowne of immortall glory.</p>
            <p>Was not likewiſe that Royall King <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, the great late French King, in edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and profeſſion a Proteſtant, and though he might afterwards (to preuent ciuill broiles, and inteſtine and vnnaturall warres in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, for the peace of the Kingdome, for the ſafety of his Subiects) let policy a little get the vpper hand of Piety, and did ſomewhat conniue and fauour the Romiſh Religion; yet
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12264:65"/>no doubt hee did neuer truly affect it. And howſoeuer ſome blacke-mouthed monſters are not aſhamed to ſay, that he was like the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> neither hot nor cold, yet charity and equity may depoſe, that he did not like to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which forſooke her firſt loue.</p>
            <p>No ſurely, but though in externall ſhew he might countenance the Popes Prelates, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard moſt of the Princes of his Countrey were of that factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yet we may ſay of him, as it is ſaid of <hi>Dauid,</hi> his heart was with God; &amp; no doubt his ſoule ſoared vpon the wings of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants profeſſion vnto the hill of God, Mount <hi>Sion;</hi> In ſo much, as that curſed murtherer <hi>Raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lack,</hi> though he might wound him mortally, yet could not kill him eternally, but God did turne the hate of that monſter of men, or rather Furie of hell, to the well-fare of this mighty Monarch, who did but leaue a crowne of thornes to gaine a Crowne of glory, who did but loſe a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſubiect to ſo many alterations (by time and troubles) to finde a Monarchy ſubiect to no mutability.</p>
            <p>Oh happy <hi>Henrie,</hi> if thou hadſt neuer beene the nouriſher of ſuch a viperous brood, which
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:12264:65"/>haue eaten out the bowels of thee which was thy foſter-Father. Oh, had the valour of thy ſoule beene equall to the courage of thy minde, thy Countrey had neuer beene wounded ſo much by thy loſſe, nor thou by that monſter; but thou hadſt bleſſed it with a longer life, and a more timely death. Oh happy, if thou hadſt laboured to haue purged Gods floore, and rooted out theſe tares out of Gods field; for had not theſe tares ſtood, the teares of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row had not ſo ouerflowne thy Kingdomes, whiles thou didſt valiantly profeſſe and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Goſpell of Chriſt. How ſecure and free thou wert from danger: How ſecure in thy eſtate, and how did all things fall out proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous to thee? How vainely did theſe King-killing Caitiffes attempt to hurt thee? No ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the loue of God did ſhield thee from all thy enemies, but when thou ſhewedſt too little loue to God, in throwing too many fauours vpon them, then the Lord did ſhew thee, that the effects of thy loue to them was their hate to thee.</p>
            <p>For the father doth not alwayes beget a childe like himſelfe; no more hath loue alwaies birth from affection: God did take away the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12264:66"/>guard of his protection and the bulwarke of his defenſe, expoſing thy breſt to an open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, both to himſelfe and thee. Wheras Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who beyond the valour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of her ſex, maintained and continued the Chriſtian Religion: How many dangerous treaſons did the hand of the Lord conduct Her thorow, and ſtill Shee was preſerued? For the Deuill and his inſtruments are like the Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile, which flyes if a man purſues it, but purſues if a man perſiſt not in his purſuit; Or as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the which if a man flies will follow him, but if hee run after it, will run from him. In a word, God no doubt brought that famous pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King, <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, to eternall durable life, through the purgatorie of a ſharpe and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den death: So doth the Phyſitian giue bitter potions, to procure the better health: So doth the Chyrurgian launce the wound, to heale the ſore; ſo are ſharpe copperas waters giuen to ſalue ſore blinded eyes; ſo is the ground har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed to make it fruitfull; and ſo no doubt God ſuffered this affliction of ſudden death, to be effected by that curſed hand, that He might be more ſound in his ſoules reſolution, that his eyes might be opened, to ſee the ſorditie of the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:12264:66"/>Popiſh Ieſuiticall Sect, and that Hee might bee better inſtructed by their crueltie in his death, than He could by their flatterie his life, who ſhewed themſelues true <hi>Abſolons,</hi> who the more <hi>Dauid</hi> did reſpect him, the more hee rebelled againſt him: Is it poſſible then that her minde can euer loſe the impreſſion of her fathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance? And can Shee remember Him, and yet forget his death? Or can reminiſcence retaine his death, and not thinke of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it? Or can the inſtrument of that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be in her memorie, and the ſetters on work of that wicked Inſtrument, the Inſtigatours of that bloudie Butcher, to that beaſtly, curſed, cruell fact, be out of her minde? And can Shee remember them, and not abhorre them? And can She abhorre them, and not relinquiſh their religion, which hold that lawfull, which Gods Law hath forbidden? For God prohibiteth the murther of any priuate perſon; but theſe Doctors maintaine it to be lawfull to kill Kings, which are publique perſons. Neither doe they permit it as a worke not impious, but perſwade men to it, as a deed meritorious: For <hi>Rauilack</hi> had no ſooner playd his part in that bloudie Scene, but hee was ſo confident in the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12264:67"/>of the act, as hee thought immediately to haue flowne to Heauen, and beene crowned a Saint by God, as well as canonized a Saint by the Pope: Such is the leauen of the Popiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that ſowres all the ſubiects of the Prince which doth profeſſe it. For what treacherous attempt againſt any King, either Proteſtant or Papiſt, hath beene made by a Proteſtant in our memories? Oh no, we are taught to feare God, to honour the King; wee muſt follow <hi>Dauids</hi> example to <hi>Saul,</hi> not lift vp our hands againſt the Lords Anointed; wee know Hee is Gods Vice-Gerent, placed there by God, and therfore to be diſplaced by none but Him: But on the contrarie, what plots haue beene laid? What treaſons haue beene committed, either for the deſtruction of a King, or ſubuerſion of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in which the Papiſts haue not only been Parties, but principall Agents? Who were they which plotted ſo many treaſons againſt the Perſon of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but Papiſts? But what treaſons were plotted againſt Queene <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> by any Proteſtant, notwithſtanding ſhee was a cruell perſecutor of that Profeſſion? What was <hi>Gowrie</hi> that conſpired the ouerthrow of the Sacred Maieſtie of King <hi>Iames,</hi> but a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt?
<pb facs="tcp:12264:67"/>What were the plotters of that horrid Gun-powder Treaſon, who ſought with one puffe to blow away both the Prince and Peeres of our Kingdome, but all profeſſors of the Romiſh Religion? What was hee which mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third of France, but a Papiſt Iacobin? In a word, what treaſons haue beene committed, which are contained in the Regiſter-booke of mans memorie, which haue not beene plotted and performed by them? And no maruell the Prieſts and people practiſe it, ſince they preach it; and it is an orthodoxall opinion and poſition amongſt them, that the Pope hath power both to diſpoſe of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and depoſe Kings, and that King-killing is not onely a lawfull, but a holy and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble calling. Who then can ſuſpect, that a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of her peereleſſe part, of her pious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, of her matchleſſe vnderſtanding and diſcretion, doth affect truly that religion, which doth infect the hearts of Princes ſubiects, which doth teach men to be monſters in gouernment, and not to ſubiect themſelues to higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but to rebell againſt the rule and authoritie of the Regall Scepter? How can thoſe Princes haue any peace with God, that doe ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
<pb facs="tcp:12264:68"/>and much hazard their liues, as to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and foſter ſuch murtherous rebellious minded men in their Kingdomes? How can Princes haue any peace with men, when they ſuffer men which are ſo wicked, to preach ſuch doctrine, and practiſe ſuch villanie? How can they haue any peace within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they may iuſtly feare that each one which ſmiles in their face, may ſmite their heart? when they nouriſh vp ſuch vipers in their boſome, as are readie each moment to eat out their bowels? How can then this Royall Princeſſe affect that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or the profeſſors of it, which was the death of her Father and his Predeceſſor? which may be a diſturbance to the peace of her Prince, and the ſafetie of his perſon, if it be tolerated? which may impaire the ſecuritie of her poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who are neuer like to poſſeſſe their Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in peace, vnleſſe ſuch vermine bee hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of their Territories; for peace and ſuch people cannot inhabit in one Kingdome, or dwell together, no more than wine and poyſon in a cryſtall glaſſe, but the glaſſe will bee broke, and the wine ſpilt and ſpoiled: If then a Prince will poſſeſſe his ſoule and ſoueraigntie in peace, he muſt baniſh theſe breakers and diſturbers of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12264:68"/>it. Neither is it a ſtrange or vnheard of matter, for France and England to ſhake hands of ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and vnitie in thoſe bleſſed Contracts; for ſince almoſt the beginning of either Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, there haue beene continually theſe friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fortunate interchanges of mariage: For it was not concealed from our Anceſtors, how beneficiall peace was betweene France and England; therefore <hi>Steuen</hi> Earle of Bloys was linked in the bond of mariage w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Adela,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour. And on the other ſide, <hi>William Waren</hi> Earle of Surrey, ſonne of <hi>Gunred,</hi> daughter to <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, maried the daughter of <hi>Hugh Vermandoys,</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the King of France. For in like manner, <hi>William</hi> Duke of Normandie did marrie <hi>Marie,</hi> daughter to <hi>Foulke</hi> Earle of Anjou; <hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſſe was linked in mariage with <hi>Iefferie Plantaginet</hi> Earle of Anjou. And for the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Kingdome, the tranquillitie of his Countrey, and felicitie of his Countrey-men, <hi>Steuen</hi> King of England maried <hi>Conſtance,</hi> daughter to the King of France. <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond maried <hi>Elenor,</hi> ſole heire to <hi>William</hi> Duke of Aquitaine. <hi>Henrie,</hi> ſonne to King <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſecond, maried <hi>Margaret,</hi> daughter to <hi>Lewis</hi> the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12264:69"/>French King. <hi>Richard Cordelion</hi> maried <hi>Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> daughter to <hi>Sanches</hi> King of Nauarre. <hi>Iohn</hi> King of England maried <hi>Iſabel,</hi> daughter and heire of <hi>Amorie</hi> Earle of Angouleſme. <hi>Arthur,</hi> nephew to King <hi>Iohn,</hi> maried the daughter of <hi>Philip</hi> King of France. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the daughter of <hi>Philip</hi> King of France. <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> daughter to <hi>Edward</hi> the third, maried <hi>Ingel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram de Guiſnes,</hi> Earle of Soyſſon and Bedford. <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond maried <hi>Iſabel,</hi> daughter to <hi>Charles</hi> the French King. <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Iane,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Philip</hi> the third King of Nauarre. <hi>Henrie</hi> the fifth maried <hi>Catherine,</hi> daughter to <hi>Charles</hi> the French King. <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixth maried <hi>Margaret,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Reiner Valois</hi> Duke of Anjou. <hi>Marie</hi> daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth, maried <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth, French King. <hi>Charles</hi> Prince of Great Britaine, betrothed to <hi>Maria Henrette,</hi> daughter to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the fourth, and ſiſter to <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth, Kings of France.</p>
            <p>Thus hath there been a long and ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of bleſſed Contracts between France and England, fortunate in each mariage, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing peace and plentie to each Dominion: ſo haue theſe matches beene proſperous to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12264:69"/>ſo is this like to bee to future ages, that all happineſſe to either Kingdom ſhall be the iſſue of this moſt longed for and liked Vnion: For who can bee made more happie in themſelues, more bleſſed in their people, than this Prince and Princeſſe, who are ſo like in themſelues, and their Countries, their people, their loues, &amp; their vertues, as this rare Ladie and her Prince? who by his ſupreme vertues, might ſeeme only to challenge Her; and Shee, for her exquiſite qualities, to enioy Him: So that from this Match may be deriued all happineſſe, and all fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie; as alſo all vertues ioyne in them; for hath his greateſt indignation and choler beene euer made a crime againſt them, whom Hee hath hated? No, no, but his royall Soule, which had nothing in it but courage, ſeemed to faile in his reuenge, and though that with the eyes of his minde He may apprehend offences, yet his mercie is as readie to forget them, as his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to apprehend them. And for his valour, I doubt not, but hereafter as well as in times paſt, the eyes of all men ſhall ſee it, and eares conceiue it, and ſucceeding ages ſhall publiſh his preſent valour; and it is not to bee feared that this aſſertion ſhall need confirmation, ſince
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:12264:70"/>there is hope it is not only without conteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but compariſon, who hath alſo clemency ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his courage, &amp; hath as much pleaſure in pardoning, as glory in vanquiſhing: ſo that it is to be expected, that as the acts of the one ſhall be ſigned with bloud, ſo the other ſhall be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with teares.</p>
            <p>And for his pious life, the world knowes that he hath no ſuperiors, few equals, but mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of inferiours; who as if he made it his onely happineſſe to ſerue God, doth only pleaſe himſelfe in pleaſing him, eſteeming his ſeruices his greateſt freedome, and deeming it a thing moſt vnworthy, to bee a Soueraigne of men, and not a ſeruant of God. And a thing moſt requiſite in a Prince to be as eminent in grace, as in place; and in vertue, as in dignity; than the which there cannot be a greater honour, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which doth more proue or improue the ſtocke He came of, who is like pure pearly water flowing from a Cryſtall fountaine; or like an Apple of gold hanging vpon a goodly Cedar, which brancheth it ſelfe into all the parts of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>For how royally deſcended, and neerely alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is He; for how frequent haue the interchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:12264:70"/>of Mariages with England, and other the chiefeſt and nobleſt Families of Chriſtendome, being the onely ſonne of <hi>Iames</hi> the ſixt of that name, King of Great-Britaine, France, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, lineally deſcended from multitudes of moſt mighty Monarchs, the vndoubted Heire of the ſaid Dominions, being iſſued from <hi>Marie</hi> Queene of Scotland, and Dowager of <hi>Francis</hi> of Valoys the ſecond French King, who depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this life 1586, marrying <hi>Henrie Steward</hi> Lord <hi>Darnely</hi> her ſecond Husband, eldeſt Son to <hi>Mathew</hi> created Duke of Albany, in <hi>an.</hi> 1565, and ſlaine in the yeare 1566: the which Q. <hi>Mary</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Iames Steward</hi> the 5. king of Scotland, whoſe firſt wife was <hi>Magdalen</hi> daughter of <hi>Francis</hi> the 1. French king, who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the yeare 1541: The which <hi>Iames</hi> the 5. was deſcended from <hi>Iames</hi> the 4. king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, who married <hi>Margaret</hi> eldeſt daughter of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the 7, and ſiſter to king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eighth, in the 11. yeare of her Fathers reigne, 1489. and was ſlaine in battle at <hi>Flowden, anno</hi> 1514, in the ſixt yeare of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the 8. his reigne. The which <hi>Iames</hi> 4. was iſſued from <hi>Iames</hi> the 3. king of Scotland, who maried <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> daughter of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the 1. king of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12264:71"/>marke, who was deſcended from <hi>Iames Steward</hi> the 2. King of Scotland, who maried <hi>Marie</hi> daughter of <hi>Arnold</hi> Duke of <hi>Gelders,</hi> and was ſlaine <hi>anno</hi> 1460, who was ſprung from the loynes of <hi>Iames Steward</hi> the firſt king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, who maried <hi>Ioane</hi> daughter of <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Summerſet:</hi> In the which England and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in thoſe times alſo gaue the kiſſes of peace in mariage; for the ſaid <hi>Ioane</hi> was deſcended from <hi>Iohn Plantagenet,</hi> ſirnamed of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> called king of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> who maried three wiues, and died in <hi>anno</hi> 1398. being iſſued from the royall ſtocke of <hi>Edward Plantagenet</hi> the 3. king of England and France, who quartered the Armes, erected the Order of the Garter, maried <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nault,</hi> and deceaſed <hi>anno</hi> 1377.</p>
            <p>But to returne vnto our former diſcourſe, this <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt was iſſued from the loynes of <hi>Robert Steward</hi> the third king of Scotland, ſometimes called <hi>Iohn,</hi> maried <hi>Annibell</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Iohn Drummond,</hi> and dyed in <hi>anno</hi> 1406, who was deſcended from <hi>Robert Steward</hi> the 2, who after <hi>Dauid Bruiſe</hi> 1370. was king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, whoſe ſecond wife was <hi>Elizabeth</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Adam Marre</hi> knight, who dyed 1309.
<pb facs="tcp:12264:71"/>was deſcended from <hi>Gualter Steward</hi> Lord Steward of Scotland, who maried <hi>Margerie</hi> daughter of <hi>Robert Bruiſe,</hi> ſiſter and heire to <hi>Dauid-Bruiſe,</hi> both kings of Scotland, by which meanes the royall name of the <hi>Stewards</hi> was matcht into the bloud royall, and made appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant heires of the Crowne; in which worthy and noble Name it doth ſtill vnto this preſent day continue. Which honourable and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be reuerenced Name, was firſt aduanced to the dignity of Lord Stewardſhip by king <hi>Malchol</hi> the 3. who conferred that honour vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Walter</hi> borne in Wales, at his returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Scotland, for ſome memorable and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſeruices which hee performed. But they were intituled in the Crowne by the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the aboueſaid <hi>Margerie,</hi> daughter to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bruiſe</hi> Earle of Carrick, the firſt king of Scotland, who maried <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſiſter to the Earle of Marre, and died in <hi>anno</hi> 1329. Whoſe Anceſtour <hi>Robert Bruiſe</hi> Lord of the Valley of <hi>Anandie</hi> in Scotland, and <hi>Cunnington</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, maried <hi>Martha</hi> daughter to the Earle of Carrick. Hee alſo married <hi>Iſabel</hi> the ſiſter and co-heire of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Scot, Earle of Cheſter, who brought vnto him <hi>Cunnington</hi> in England for
<pb facs="tcp:12264:72"/>her Dowry, being of the ſtocke of <hi>Dauid</hi> Earle of <hi>Angus</hi> and <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> the 3. ſonne of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> Prince of Scotland, who married <hi>Margaret</hi> daughter and coheire of the Earle of Cheſter, and dyed in <hi>anno</hi> 12 19. <hi>William</hi> king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (ſirnamed the Lion) ſecond Son of Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> ſucceeded his brother king <hi>Malchol</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1160, and dyed without iſſue. <hi>Henrie</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntingdon</hi> married <hi>Ada</hi> the daughter of <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Werren,</hi> hauing a period prefixt to his daies by the Almighty, afore the expiration of his Fathers life <hi>anno</hi> 1152. <hi>Dauid</hi> the firſt king of Scotland, ſonne of <hi>Malchol,</hi> married <hi>Maud</hi> daughter and heire of <hi>Waltheof</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> and dyed in <hi>anno</hi> 1153. in the 19. yeare of the Reigne of king <hi>Steuen;</hi> ſo <hi>Maud</hi> Queene of England, daughter of <hi>Malchol,</hi> and brother to <hi>Dauid</hi> the firſt king of Scotland, was eſpouſed to <hi>Henrie</hi> the firſt king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſonne to <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, who dyed <hi>anno</hi> 1119, from whoſe loynes ſprung the famous race of the Brittiſh Kings, who haue for their valour, and their fortunes beene famous, and admired throughout the world.</p>
            <p>Neither was here a beginning of the loue and amitie betweene them, who now by one are
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:12264:72"/>for euer made one: For likewiſe before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt there was a mutual exchange of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, &amp; betweene the ancient famous Saxons, and our pious Kings &amp; Princes anceſtors, haue bin famous matches for the good &amp; benefit of both Kingdomes, for both the Lines of <hi>Egbert</hi> the Saxon K. of England, &amp; <hi>Alphin</hi> K. of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, met in the mariage of <hi>Malchol</hi> the 3, and <hi>Margaret</hi> ſiſter of <hi>Edgar Ehelin</hi> right heire to the Crowne of England, who died <hi>an.</hi> 1093. Which <hi>Malchol</hi> was the ſon of <hi>Duncan,</hi> who vanquiſht <hi>Mackboth</hi> in fight, yet afterwards himſelfe was ſlaine in <hi>anno</hi> 1092, whoſe Father <hi>Dunken</hi> the 1. king of Scotland, (&amp; heire of <hi>Beatrix</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Malchol</hi>) was ſlaine by <hi>Makbeth</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1046. <hi>Beatrix</hi> eldeſt daughter, and co-heire of king <hi>Malchol</hi> the 2, was maried to <hi>Abineth Crinathany</hi> of the Weſt Ilands of Scotland. <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol</hi> the ſecond king of Scotland, ſonne of <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> the 3, ſubdued king <hi>Trim,</hi> was ſlaine in <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1034. <hi>Kenneth</hi> the third king of Scotland, ſucceeded king <hi>Culen,</hi> became a tyrant, and was murthered 994. <hi>Malchol</hi> the firſt ſonne of king <hi>Donald,</hi> was the ſucceſſour of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the 3, and was murthered in the yeare 958. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nald</hi> the ſixt king of Scotland, next after king
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:12264:73"/>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> was his predeceſſour, who died <hi>anno</hi> 904. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the ſecond, king of Scotland, after the death of <hi>Donald</hi> his Vnckle, was ſlaine in <hi>anno</hi> 874. <hi>Keneth</hi> the ſecond, king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, called the great, ſucceeded his Father king <hi>Alphen,</hi> and died in <hi>anno</hi> 894. <hi>Alphin</hi> ſonne of K. <hi>Achai,</hi> who made the firſt league w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>France,</hi> after the death of king <hi>Dongallies,</hi> hee likewiſe recouered the kingdome of Scotland <hi>anno</hi> 830, and was afterwards ſlaine in <hi>anno</hi> 834.</p>
            <p>This is the royall deſcent of our renowned Prince by the Fathers ſide, being ſprung by the Fathers and Grandfathers ſide, from ſo many glorious ſtemmes of the kings of Scotland. By the Grandmother from the renowned race of the Kings of England, to whom Scotland hath beene often lincked by the performance of Hymens rites, and the celebration of happie nuptials; but now it hath found (by the meanes of our gracious Soueraigne) a more bleſſed and aſſured vnion. Whoſe anceſtours (the true ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of admiration) haue euer beene famous for vertuous actions, for what haue they beene defectiue in which ſauoured of perfection? what worth haue they wanted, that might make them eſteemed to bee the moſt noble
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12264:73"/>worthies that euer liued? For he hath beeneal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed to ſo many mighty Kings of England and Scotland; and in fine, doth heire rightfully the vertues and renownes of both Kings and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; for who can be ſilent but dumbe men in his praiſes? or can any be tongue-tide whoſe heart is lincked to him by the bond of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? and can any one which is a true ſubiect but make ſuch a Soueraigne the ſubiect of his praiſes, and obiect of his duty? But to the intent that all may know the highneſſe of this Princes birth, as well as the goodneſſe of his minde, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine but the greatneſſe of his anceſtours and allyes of the mothers ſide, whoſe remembrance to vs is like Myrrhe vnto the body which it embalmeth, incorruptible, but wonderous bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for how can it bee better then bitter vnto vs, ſeeing it reduceth into our reminiſcence her Name which was ſo delightfull, seeing that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs in minde of her perfections, the which making vs ſee how neceſſary ſhe was for vs, manifeſts vnto vs how miſerable we are for her. Oh no, it is impoſſible for vs to remember her, and to forget her vertues; or to retaine the loſſe of them in our minds, and to forget ſorrow, but to haue weeping eies and bleeding hearts; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:12264:74"/>that the perpetual welfare of England required that ſhe had bin immortall, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe death our griefe hath birth, and from whoſe tombe floweth our ſorrow. But why ſhould I thus produce this mournful diſh at this mariage feaſt, vnleſſe it ſhould be like ſowre ſawces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beget vs better ſtomackes to our ſweeter dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to make the beautie of our ſolace more amorous and excellent by the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the paleneſſe of our ſorrow: So doth a faire ſtately Steede ſeeme moſt to bee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med being amongſt a number of ill-fauoured Iades. So doth it ſerue as well as a painting for a faire Lady to haue a foule Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid; ſo doth a paſſionate ſpeech delight in a pleaſant Comedie, and a ſorrowfull paſſage thruſt in amongſt a company of merrie ſcenes. And no doubt this ſerues like the face of a blacke-Moore to his teeth, makes them ſeeme more white and comely.</p>
            <p>This ſorrow, for the loſſe of our Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> makes our ioy, for the enioying of this Princeſſe, the greater; who is like her for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as She ſeemeth moſt fortunate, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wife of ſuch a Prince, deſcended from ſuch a mother, who although dead, yet liue in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:12264:74"/>Her, as being the true Mirrour of her moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious qualities; He alſo moſt happie in Her, in finding a kinde of a mother in a wife, ſo like Her, who may ſerue Him for his mothers pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, all times to looke on, with a reſpectiue, louing, ioyfull remembrance, to ſee his mother liuing in Her: For ſurely, her beautie and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue cannot die, ſo long as this famous Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſe ſhall liue. And thus, like <hi>Iſaak</hi> with <hi>Rebecca,</hi> Hee ſhall bee comforted after the death of his mother, who for the goodneſſe and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her bloud, was almoſt vnparalleld; For how many royall Kings, which weilded their regall Scepters with policie, power, and pietie, is Shee deſcended from? How neerely allied was She to multitudes of potent Princes? in ſo much, as walls of friendſhip were erected by her meanes, round about theſe Kingdomes, as the King of Denmarke, who for his place and perſon, is both wealthie and worthie, and able, both for men and money, to raiſe a friend, or ruine an enemie; but howſoeuer, to defend an Allie, who was the naturall and moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate brother of our moſt royall Queene, who by this moſt happie Contract, is vnited to France, as we to Him, who will be alwayes in
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12264:75"/>readineſſe to doe any office of friendſhip and fraternitie vnto it.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſpeake of the Anceſtors of our Queene, as <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond, King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, Norway, Goths, and Vandalls, ſonne to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the third, who died in that menacing memorable yeere 1588. and the 32. of the reigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of neuer-dying fame and memorie, who maried <hi>Sophia</hi> (not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily ſo called, in reſpect her diſpoſition did anſwer her denomination; for indeed Shee was all wiſdome, as her name importeth) Queene of Denmarke, ſole heire to <hi>Vlrick</hi> Duke of Meckleburg, in <hi>anno</hi> 1572. from whoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed loynes and fruitfull, as from a fertile Soyle, hath flowed ſuch a noble Progenie, as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to promiſe to people the world with Princes, as that Princely, royall, religious, pious, prudent Queen <hi>Anne,</hi> the moſtreſpected, chaſte, meeke, mercifull, Maieſtique Wife of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Maieſtie of our moſt mightie Monarch, <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt; and the moſt happie Mother of our moſt promiſing Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> the Felicitie of his Father, and the Pledge of our ſucceeding Peace, &amp; the Propagation of Religion; &amp; alſo the fortunate Mother of many hopefull Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:12264:75"/>the moſt Gracious Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> hath borne vnto <hi>Frederick</hi> King of Bohemia. Alſo the aforenamed <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the fourth, the now King of Denmarke, who maried <hi>Anne Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> Queene of Denmarke, daughter to <hi>Ioachim Frederick</hi> Marquiſſe of Brandenburg, borne in <hi>anno</hi> 1575. who hath now reaped the fruits and pledges of his mariage-bed, the moſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and worthie Prince, <hi>Frederick Chriſtian</hi> Heire of Norway, Duke of Holſt and Sleſwick, and is ſtill ſuruiuing, a moſt proſperous, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and honourable Prince: As alſo <hi>Vlrick,</hi> Heire of Norway, Duke of Holſt, Knight of the noble order, Brother to Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> and Vnckle to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> ſecond ſonne of King <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond: And in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of Holſt and Sleſwick, Brother to Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> and Vnckle to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> who was borne 1583. and died vnmaried in Muſcouia. Alſo <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> eldeſt Daughter of King <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, Siſter to Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> and Aunt to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> who was eſpouſed to <hi>Henrie Iulio</hi> Duke of Brunſwicke and Luneburg, father of two brothers, the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Duke of Brunſwicke and Luneburg, and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Duke of Brunſwicke and Biſhop of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:12264:76"/>Halberſtadt, who hath manifeſted his infinite loue and courage, for the defenſe of the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and his Allies, expoſing his breſt to open dangers and infinite perils, hazarding his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and himſelfe, beyond ordinarie valour or vertue, for the reſtoring of his ſo much beloued, and ſo much worthie to bee beloued kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> O worthie Prince! neuer enough to be commended by the weakneſſe of a humane pen; for I thinke no <hi>Tullian,</hi> no ſurely, nor <hi>Tertullian</hi> eloquence, could ſufficiently compile thy commendations: and I doubt not, but thy vertues haue engrauen more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thoughts on Thee, in the hearts of all, than can be expreſſed by the hands of any. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the famous Off-ſpring of this happie King <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond: and not to forget <hi>Auguſta,</hi> third daughter to King <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, and Siſter to Queene <hi>Anne,</hi> and Aunt to our worthie Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> borne in the yeere of Chriſt 1580. <hi>Hedwige,</hi> fourth and youngeſt daughter to King <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Siſter to Queen <hi>Anne,</hi> and Aunt to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> maried to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Duke Elector of Saxonie, Marquiſſe of Miſmia; all which Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces isſued from the loynes, and are the poſteritie
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12264:76"/>of the famous King <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Sophia</hi> his chaſte Spouſe and worthie Wife. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the third, King of Denmarke, &amp;c. ſonne to <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt, King of Denmarke, who maried <hi>Dorothie</hi> Queene of Denmarke, daughter to <hi>Magnes</hi> the ſecond, Duke of Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Angry, and Weſtphaly. <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt, King of Denmarke, maried <hi>Sophia</hi> of Pomer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Queene of Denmarke, his ſecond wife, daughter to <hi>Bugſlane</hi> the tenth, by <hi>Anne</hi> of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the firſt, King of Denmarke, &amp;c. maried <hi>Dorothie</hi> Queene of Denmarke, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Iohn</hi> Marquiſſe of Brandenburg, widow of <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Palatine of Rhine. <hi>Theodore</hi> the fortunate, Earle of Holdenburg, maried <hi>Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wige</hi> his ſecond wife, daughter of <hi>Gerard</hi> Duke of Sleſwicke. <hi>Henrie</hi> the elder, Duke of Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke and Lunenburg, was maried to <hi>Catherine</hi> of Pomerland, Dutcheſſe of Brunſwick. <hi>Albert,</hi> ſirnamed the <hi>Achilles</hi> of Germanie, Marquiſſe of Brandenburg, maried <hi>Margaret</hi> Marchioneſſe of Brandenburg, youngeſt daughter of <hi>Iames</hi> Marquiſſe of Baden. <hi>Fredericke</hi> Earle of Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lern, Burgraue of Norrenburg, maried <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of Bauaria, daughter of the Duke of Bauaria, who died in the yeere 1457. <hi>Fredericke</hi> the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:12264:77"/>Hardie, Landtgraue of Thurin, maried the daughter of <hi>Henrie</hi> Earle of Henneburg. <hi>Iames</hi> Marquiſſe of Baden, Earle of Spanheim, maried <hi>Catherine</hi> the daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine. <hi>Henrie</hi> the firſt, Earle of Holſt and Scaumburg, maried <hi>Agnes</hi> daughter of <hi>Florence</hi> Earle of Broncherſteine. <hi>Albert</hi> of Habsburg, Arch-Duke of Auſtria and Emperour, maried <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of Carinthia, who was murthered 1308. <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt, Palatine Elector of Rhine, Duke of Bauaria, maried <hi>Agnes</hi> daughter of <hi>Henrie,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Henrie Leo. Lewis</hi> Duke of Bauaria maried <hi>Lowiſa,</hi> daughter of <hi>Primiſlay</hi> King of Bohemia, widdow of <hi>Albert Boggai,</hi> and died in 1231. <hi>Henrie Bureuen,</hi> Prince of the Obotrites &amp; Meckel, maried <hi>Maud</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Henrie Leo,</hi> Elector of Saxonie. <hi>Otho</hi> the Rich, Earle of Aſcanie, Marquiſſe of Saliſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, maried <hi>Helica</hi> daughter of <hi>Beling</hi> the Great, Elector of Saxonie. So likewiſe <hi>Squantiber</hi> the firſt, Prince of Vandalls, Sclauonie, Duke of Pomerand and Stetin, one of the prime Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors and Roots of theſe royall Branches, died in the yeere of Chriſt 1107. being the firſt yeere of the reigne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the firſt of England.</p>
            <p>Here then the blindeſt man may ſee the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12264:77"/>Genealogie of our mightie Prince, the which I haue related in a compendious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, fearing to be tedious or troubleſome; yet not ſo briefly, but it is void of obſcuritie; ſo that the moſt ignorant may conceiue the moſt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious mariages, betweene the Anceſtors of this Royall Prince, and all parts of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For the Progenitors of his deere Father, and our dread Soueraigne, haue matched into the moſt famous Families of the houſe of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, French King, and of Nauarre, Arragon, Caſtile, Loraine, and Hapsburg, now called Auſtria, of the Emperour, and King of Spaine.</p>
            <p>Alſo by the way, the houſes of Luxenburgh, Gelders, and Dowglaſſe, all the which manifeſt vnto thee how often they haue beene graced with the participation and ioyning in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall ſtemme of his ſacred Maieſty, the King of Great-Britaine.</p>
            <p>Alſo the noble Line out of which ſprung the Kings of Denmarke, as Saxonie, Pommerland, Brunſwicke, Plantagenet, Oldenburg, Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, Holſt, and Sleſwicke, Zelerne, and being deſcended from the Electors of Brandenburg, Bauare, and Mackleburg, in former times the Kings of the Orbotrites. Alſo you may ſee Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12264:78"/>Baden, Oldenburg, Thurin, Bohemia. Alſo the houſe of Auſtria ſpringeth forth from Poland, that her branch might be inoculated into Pomerland, and ſo be grafted into Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markes ſtocke. This is the neuer-enough to be illuſtrated deſcent of our moſt royall Prince, whoſe famous Predeceſſours and Allies doe, like ſo many burning Lamps, ſhine to keepe his vertues from obſcurity; but that being ſo high of birth all men might looke vpon and loue his worthy diſpoſition and pious inclination, the which, if I ſhould offer to produce vpon the Theater &amp; Stage of theſe my labours, it would be too little to be contained in it, and I could not tell where to make a Prologue or an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to my ſtorie. Oh no, let ſuch ambition be as remote once to thinke, or vndertake to penne his praiſes to the full, which deſires no praiſe, but deſerues all: Let it only be my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that I haue payd ſome duty to him, vnto whoſe perfections my affections are deuoted, and whoſe I am. Millions of times more then my owne, of whoſe worth I am an admirer, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe Highneſſe it is my onely deſire to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my ſeruice, and manifeſt my duty; and likewiſe to that high borne Royall Princeſſe,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:12264:78"/>his intended and contracted Spouſe, whoſe Royall Perſon includes all high beatitudes: for her birth is moſt excellent, and yet her fortune exceeds her birth, and alſo her vertues her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, whoſe beauty darkens the beames of mundane luſter, &amp; draweth all humane lights to it, to behold it with admiration.</p>
            <p>Alas, what ſhall I ſay? If I ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſuch an endleſſe enterpriſe, as to expreſſe her vertues to the full, which are aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, except I ſhould take in hand a taske infinit; for her praiſes muſt bee infinite, becauſe her worth is ſuch, and ſure I am my worke is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in nothing but weakneſſe; let me therfore haue leaue to make that the <hi>Omega</hi> which was the <hi>Alpha</hi> of my worke, and end with that with the which I did begin, humbly beſſeeching the Giuer of all good gifts, and Father of lights, in whom is no variablenes or ſhadow of turning, to bleſſe this Vnion with a happy proceſſe, which he hath happily begunne, to make their vertues permanent which now are peereleſſe, and (howſoeuer man can ſcarcely conceiue how they ſhould be more vertuous) yet that they may ſtill increaſe and grow in goodneſſe, in which there is euermore a <hi>plus vltra.</hi> Long
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:12264:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>may they liue and loue together, and bring forth ſuch golden Apples of Poſterity, and haue ſuch a happy off-ſpring, that they may be iuſtly ioyous, and all the world fortunate in it, that they may haue length and proſperity of dayes here, Peace at the time of their paſſage out of this world, and a happy reſurrection to eternall life; the which, that it may be, let all good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects ſay as I pray, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12264:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
